<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Into Resurrection</title>
        <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com</link>
        <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 08:59:57 -0500</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-20-2017-neuroscience-humanities</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-20-2017-neuroscience-humanities</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Neuroscience and the Humanities: A Meditation</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/brain.jpg" alt="brain scan" />
<figcaption>Visualization of a DTI measurement of a human brain | © 2006 Thomas Schultz | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:DTI-sagittal-fibers.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en">CC BY-SA 3.0</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>By happy coincidence, last week I was reading both Cordelia Fine&rsquo;s <em>Delusions of Gender</em> and Marilynne Robinson&rsquo;s essay collection <em>The Givenness of Things</em>, which begins with &ldquo;Humanism.&rdquo; In this essay, Robinson considers the limitations of neuroscience, which she describes as reducing the intricate complexity of the brain to &ldquo;an essentially simple thing.&rdquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> This reduction, in Robinson&rsquo;s analysis, rejects the notion of the self and ultimately results in a devaluation of humanity.</p>

<p>Cordelia Fine&rsquo;s book is a little less intellectually lofty, but she also takes popular neuroscience to task, specifically for oversimplifying and overstating complex and often unclear results about differences between men and women. Fine&rsquo;s more narrow argument supports Robinson&rsquo;s larger point: when neuroscience is used to support sweeping generalizations about gender differences, both men and women are dehumanized, their potentials and limitations reduced to electrical impulses in their brains.</p>

<p>Fine argues, repeatedly, that a focus on the brain alone erases the many social factors that lead men and women to behave and respond differently — in other words, neuroscientists tend to study brains as isolated rather than embedded in complex social networks. Reading Fine in conjunction with Robinson, we can thus criticize the tendencies of neuroscience, or at the very least reporting on neuroscience, to ignore the impact of both sociology and the humanities on our understanding of the self.</p>

<p>But why does this tendency to view the brain in isolation from society and the humanities matter? After all, neuroscience has the very specific goal of discovering how the brain works in a mechanical sense, exploring topics like where and how emotions manifest and whether differences exist between male and female brains. Any area of study must have its limitations, and as Robinson points out the very nature of science over the last two hundred years or so bars it from asking metaphysical questions about the soul, or even the self.</p>

<p>Fine and Robinson both take different angles on the question of why the limited focus of neuroscience is a problem, but both broadly criticize it for its overreach, the tendency to take a specific test result and make sweeping generalities about human nature. For Fine, the overreach lies in how neuroscience affirms and entrenches our tired old stereotypes of women — with the veneer of objective scientific truth but without consideration of the effect of centuries of patriarchy. For Robinson, the overreach lies in oversimplification, the notion that we can understand humanity by tracing where the brain lights up in a scanner. Both authors resist the essentializing of ourselves to the mechanisms of our brains, or at least to those mechanisms described in simple, cause-and-effect terms.</p>

<p><figure class="float-left">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Charlotte_Bronte.jpg" alt="Charlotte Bronte" />
<figcaption>Portrait of Charlotte Brontë by George Richmond, 1850 | public domain | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:CBRichmond.png">Wikimedia Commons</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Neuroscience is just the latest in an extensive human tendency to oversimplify and essentialize human beings. Long before brain scans and modern neuroscience, the author Charlotte Brontë warns against reducing complex individuals to the mere sum of their parts. In Brontë&rsquo;s novel <em>Jane Eyre</em>, Jane makes a passionate speech to Mr. Rochester in which she proclaims: &ldquo;Do you think, because I am poor, obscure, plain, and little, I am soulless and heartless? You think wrong! — I have as much soul as you, — and full as much heart!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Brontë may not have had brain scans, but she was familiar with the nineteenth-century methods of essentializing people by class and gender. Given the social norms of the day, the wealthy, upper-class, male Mr. Rochester had every reason to believe that poor, lower-class, female Jane was, indeed, lacking in soul and heart, lacking in those characteristics that make one fully human.</p>

<p>Jane&rsquo;s declaration reminds Mr. Rochester — and us, dear reader — that Jane herself, her desires and talents and emotions and capabilities, cannot be boiled down to her class, gender, and dare I say brain scans. Brontë&rsquo;s heart-wrenching narrative of Jane&rsquo;s childhood emphasizes her extraordinary passion and sensitivity despite an upbringing designed to squash those characteristics.</p>

<p>And so, despite all the inputs that should push her to develop a poor, mean character, Jane clings to a self that is kind, generous, <em>good</em>, a self that is shaped by her circumstances but not in a mechanical, cause-and-effect manner. Yet she knows that when people see her, they often see not her unique self but the presumed product of poverty, charity and femininity — a product endowed with less heart and soul than an upper-class man.</p>

<p>Neuroscience has a similar tendency, reducing the complex web of the self to a measurable series of stimuli and responses. Neuroscience has, to be sure, great value: for example, understanding how stress can reshape our brains can give us greater empathy for those who encounter the daily stress of poverty or racism.</p>

<p>But Robinson and Fine, along with all the great novelists, remind us that we cannot reduce humans to their brain chemistry. Social context matters greatly, especially since brain science is still in its infancy. Even social context, though, cannot fully account for the self. For that, we must turn to the humanities to understand what it means to have a soul, to have a heart — to have those qualities that poor, little, obscure Jane claims, qualities that make her an equal to any other human being.</p>

<p>I think most of would agree that our self is something more than the chemistry or electrical impulses in our physical brains. And to understand something as complex and metaphysical of the self, we must not limit ourselves to neuroscience. Instead, we must draw on the resources of social science and the humanities as we strive to understand what it means to be human.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Marilynne Robinson, &ldquo;Humanism&rdquo; in <em>The Givenness of Things</em> (New York: Picador, 2015), p. 6.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-18-2017-me-too</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-18-2017-me-too</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 08:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Me Too</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/chagall_adam_eve.jpeg" alt="Chagall Adam and Eve" />
<figcaption>Marc Chagall, &ldquo;Adam and Eve,&rdquo; 1912 | public domain | via <a href="https://www.wikiart.org/en/marc-chagall/adam-and-eve-1912">WikiArt</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t wanted to write about Harvey Weinstein. Not because I don&rsquo;t care, or don&rsquo;t believe the accusations, or have nothing to say, but because I&rsquo;m tired. I&rsquo;m not shocked. I&rsquo;m not surprised. I&rsquo;m horrified, of course, although that reaction is dulled by too many repetitions of the same story.</p>

<p>But with #MeToo trending on Twitter as I write today, I feel the need to say something. It&rsquo;s not going to be something profound. It&rsquo;s not going to be the something that suddenly changes things for women. But it&rsquo;s one more something on the mound of stories and arguments and pleas that, maybe, someday, will grow into change.</p>

<p>When I say me too, I know I&rsquo;m one of the lucky ones: I&rsquo;ve never been sexually assaulted. Just harassed. Just made to feel uncomfortable, just grateful to the friends — men and women — who&rsquo;ve looked out for me over the years, walking me to my car at night, warning me about the too-friendly professor, watching my drink at the bar.</p>

<p>In other words, just a typical woman.</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s the problem: I don&rsquo;t know any woman who hasn&rsquo;t experienced harassment in some form. It&rsquo;s everywhere, but that also means it&rsquo;s nowhere. Invisible.</p>

<p>Something like the allegations about Harvey Weinstein break onto the scene, and everyone is horrified. For a while. But we all know the pattern, because it happens so often: we feel outrage, but it seldom translates into an examination of why this keeps happening.</p>

<p>We start to distance ourselves. We chalk assault up to Hollywood culture. We have a hard time reconciling a genial figure peddling pudding in dorky sweaters with a habitual user of date rape drugs. We dismiss crude language about assaulting women as locker-room talk.</p>

<p>We wonder why women don&rsquo;t speak up about their experiences sooner, or louder, or somehow better. We read <a href="https://nyti.ms/2kMJV4o">op-eds</a> that suggest this sort of harassment happens to pretty women, less conservative women, women with less protective parents. We make this a liberal problem (Weinstein) or a conservative one (Roger Ailes), a worldly problem (Hugh Hefner) or a religious one (Bill Gothard).</p>

<p>As women, we are told and we tell ourselves that we&rsquo;re too sensitive, we can&rsquo;t take a joke, we&rsquo;re imagining things, we should be flattered by the attention. If we&rsquo;re careful enough, if we smile and nod, if we wear the right things and say the right things we&rsquo;ll be fine.</p>

<p>Besides, how often does that sort of thing <em>really</em> happen?</p>

<p>And before we know it, we&rsquo;re back to normal — and maybe a career has ended, but more often nothing much happens and nothing much changes.</p>

<p>If we want this cycle to change, we must confront the fact that, as a society, we value women less than men. We find their pain less important than men&rsquo;s reputations. We believe them less, we subject them to greater scrutiny, we hold them to impossibly high standards.</p>

<p>This happens in churches and faith-based organization and in Hollywood. In academia and service industries. On the coasts and in rural Iowa. In Silicon Valley, in hospitals, in the C-suite, in factories. Women are harassed and assaulted by strangers and trusted friends, by colleagues and intimate partners, by bosses and subordinates.</p>

<p>And I&rsquo;m tired of people being periodically horrified by high-profile instances of assault. I want people to be horrified that half the population has to deal with harassment on a regular basis.</p>

<p>I want outrage and official action over the professors who have inappropriate contact with their students, not just a whisper network among women.</p>

<p>I want the comedian who tells a rape joke to hear horrified gasps, not laughter.</p>

<p>I want the pastor who delivers sexist jokes from the pulpit to be corrected by his parishioners, not allowed to persist.</p>

<p>I want the manager who touches inappropriately to be reprimanded, not ignored.</p>

<p>I want the colleague who makes off-color remarks to be ostracized, not excused.</p>

<p>I want the phrase &ldquo;boys will be boys&rdquo; stricken from our vocabulary.</p>

<p>I want to stop feeling so damn thankful that I&rsquo;ve only been harassed, not assaulted.</p>

<p>But until we work up the will as a culture to value women as human beings whose worth is equal to men, none of what I want will happen.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-16-2017-la-la-land</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-16-2017-la-la-land</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 08:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>La La Land and Loss</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/lala_land.jpg" alt="La La Land" />
<figcaption>© 2016 <a href="http://www.lalaland.movie/gallery/13">Summit Entertainment</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>(Spoilers throughout)</p>

<p>I watched <em>La La Land</em> for the first time last week. At first, I wasn&rsquo;t sold: I was a little bored by the meet cute, the mutual dislike opener to the romantic relationship, the aspiring actress falling for the snobby, nostalgic lover of jazz. But the ending? That got to me.</p>

<p>I must confess that I&rsquo;m a sucker for the unresolved ending, the ending where plot threads dangle and the happily-ever-afters dissolve into uncertainty. And <em>La La Land</em> subverts the ending we expect of a romantic comedy in ways that underscore the tensions between individuals and relationships and highlight the loss that always comes with the choices we make.</p>

<p>In the final dream sequence of the film, we see Emma Stone&rsquo;s character (Mia) imagine a different path for her relationship with Sebastian (played by Ryan Gosling). The power of this dream sequence is that we, the viewers, want it to be true: the conventional romantic narrative of the majority of the film sets us up to want Mia and Sebastian to get to happily ever after together. Sebastian living alone, Mia married to another man — these do no make for a Hollywood ending. The dream sequence feels right, feels like the ending we deserve.</p>

<p>And yet. The dream sequence is a fantasy: it waves away the conflict between Mia and Sebastian, and not just the initial romantic attraction disguised as repulsion. It erases Sebastian&rsquo;s time with the band, erases his failure to come to Mia&rsquo;s one-woman show, erases their separation when Mia goes to Paris to star in a movie … and erases Sebastian&rsquo;s successful opening of his dream jazz club.</p>

<p>This dream sequence underscores the vital tension in the film between the relationship and the individual dreams of Mia and Sebastian: they can&rsquo;t have it all. They can&rsquo;t have each other while also fulfilling their separate dreams.</p>

<p><em>La La Land</em> layers the expectation of romantic comedies — that the relationship prevails — with the other prevailing film expectation that the characters follow their individual dreams. Sebastian tells Mia not to turn down the film in Paris because of him, and she doesn&rsquo;t. She ends up with the successful acting career she wanted, as well as a husband and child with whom she seems very happy. And Sebastian doesn&rsquo;t find a romantic partner, but he remains close to his sister and her family as he launches his own jazz club.</p>

<p>They have followed their dreams, they are both happy — but the final sequence underscores the cost, highlights what could have been had they made different choices. The film doesn&rsquo;t suggest that they have made wrong choices; the final look between Mia and Sebastian contains acceptance, not unhappiness. But this look also acknowledges the inevitable loss of making a choice.</p>

<p>What is the cost of pursuing your own dreams, of valuing your individuality over relationships, or even a single relationship? Is the cost worth what you gain? <em>La La Land</em> doesn&rsquo;t answer these questions, refuses to answer these questions — at the end of the film, both the future that is and the future that could have been are good. But the film forces us to ask that question.</p>

<p>Unlike most romantic comedies, where the characters either do end up having it all or where any individual loss is minimized compared to the relationship, <em>La La Land</em> forces us to consider what we value and what we lose in our choices. The film presents no solution, no formula for making these calculations. But the power of the ending lies in its acknowledgement of loss, its realization of the cost of the always inevitable choice between individual and relationship.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-13-2017-middle-age-the-ruin</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-13-2017-middle-age-the-ruin</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Poetry Interlude: The Ruin</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Hadrians_wall.jpg" alt="Hadrians wall" />
<figcaption>Hadrian&rsquo;s Wall, Northumberland | © 2008 <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/stuandsam">Stu &amp; Sam Marlow </a> | via <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/stuandsam/3049532451/in/photostream/">Flicker</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/">CC BY-ND 2.0</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>After all the medieval history, today we take an autumn-appropriate breath with some Old English poetry. The poem partially quoted below, <em>The Ruin</em>, is an elegy, a lament for things lost. Old English poetry has a rich selection of elegies, and this is one of my favorites. It comes from a tenth-century manuscript known as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exeter_Book">Exeter book</a>, the largest of only a few surviving collections of Old English literature.</p>

<p>The poem itself, in the tradition of an elegy, meditates on ruins and the inevitable decay of all earthly things. In a fittingly poetic twist, the manuscript itself is also damaged, leaving the poem about ruins in ruins.</p>

<p>In a season overrun with decorative gourds and pumpkin spice delicacies that distract us from the coming winter, it&rsquo;s worth reflecting for a moment on falls, on ends, on decay:</p>

<blockquote><p>Wondrous is this wall&rsquo;s foundation – <em>wyrd</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> has broken</p>

<p>and shattered this city; the work of giants crumbles.</p>

<p>The roofs are ruined, the towers toppled,</p>

<p>frost in the mortar has broken the gate,</p>

<p>torn and worn and shorn by the storm,</p>

<p>eaten through with age. The earth’s grasp</p>

<p>holds the builders, rotten, forgotten,</p>

<p>the hard grip of the ground, until a hundred</p>

<p>generations of men are gone.</p>

<p>This wall, rust-stained</p>

<p>and covered with moss, has endured one kingdom after another,</p>

<p>stood in the storm, steep and tall, then tumbled.</p>

<p>The foundation remains, felled by the weather,</p>

<p>it fell…..<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>grimly ground up ….</p>

<p>……cleverly created….</p>

<p>…… a crust of mud surrounded …</p>

<p>….. put together a swift</p>

<p>and subtle system of rings; one of great wisdom</p>

<p>wondrously bound the braces together with wires.</p></blockquote>

<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Vindolanda.jpg" alt="Vindolanda" />
<figcaption>Bathhouse in Vindolanda, a Roman military fort built in England in the late first century CE | image © 2007 Optimist on the run | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AVindolanda_bathhouse_-_2007-05-19.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en">CC-BY-SA-3.0</a> &amp; <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:GNU_Free_Documentation_License,_version_1.2">GFDL-1.2</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>The poem continues with descriptions of the inhabitants of this ruin, proud warriors who succumbed to plague and war despite their joy and bravery while they lived:</p>

<blockquote><p>The slain fell on all sides, plague-days came,</p>

<p>and death destroyed all the brave swordsmen;</p>

<p>the seats of their idols became empty wasteland,</p>

<p>the city crumbled, its re-builders collapsed</p>

<p>beside their shrines. So now these courts are empty,</p>

<p>and the rich vaults of the vermilion roofs</p>

<p>shed their tiles.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p></blockquote>

<p>Unlike other Old English elegies, <em>The Ruin</em> has no explicitly Christian themes, no reference to the eternal nature of God. It&rsquo;s a poem about a lost civilization (most scholars connect it to the Roman ruins in modern-day Bath), and as such a reminder that all civilizations come to an end. Reading it today, in the twenty-first century, we have an added layer of poignancy: the author and his culture have crumbled into the ruins of history, the poem itself existing in ruins — a memorial, as were the Roman ruins, to those who produced them.</p>

<p>This probably seems like an odd way to end a series that attempts to reclaim the middle ages from those who would distort them in the service of damaging ideologies. And I could have chosen any number of other cultural relics that are more up-beat, more exemplary of the rich and diverse culture of the middle ages.</p>

<p>But at the beginning of this series, I talked about the culture wars as a fight to define and defend western culture — and those actions require that we also preserve western culture. Against this urge for preservation, this poem reminds us that all things end, all things decay; winter always comes, no matter how bountiful the harvest.</p>

<p>And yet something also always remains. The inhabitants of the ruins, like the author of the poem and the copyists of the manuscript, have vanished — but the ruins, the poem, the things themselves, they survive. There is loss, yes, but memory remains. An elegy can only exist if something is remembered, is valued enough to remember.</p>

<p>Change can feel like death, like loss. And I think it&rsquo;s obvious that western culture, especially after centuries of colonization and globalization, is changing. But all things end; this is the way of the world. We may mourn the end, elegize the great monuments of the past. But someday we too will be mourned and elegized by those who come after us.</p>

<p>This knowledge can free us from the need to preserve, from the need to prevent change. And as the seasons shift, let us take a moment to contemplate the transience of the world.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>An Old English term that roughly translates to fate — but not fate as happy coincidence. This is that fate that all things must die.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>The dots represent unreadable portions of the damaged manuscript.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Translation by Roy Liuzza, from <em>Old English Poetry: An Anthology</em> (Ontario: Broadview Press, 2014), 43-44.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-11-2017-middle-ages-crusades</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-11-2017-middle-ages-crusades</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>The Crusades</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Peter_crusade.jpg" alt="Peter the Hermit" />
<figcaption>Peter the Hermit leading troops to Jerusalem <a href="http://www.bl.uk/catalogues/illuminatedmanuscripts/record.asp?MSID=2976&CollID=28&NStart=1500">(British Library MS Egerton 1500, fol. 45v, c. 1325-1350)</a> | public domain | via <a href="https://www.britannica.com/media/full/453856/74209">Encyclopedia Britannica</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>So far in this series on white supremacy and the middle ages, we&rsquo;ve established that medieval Europe was not <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-part-2a">&ldquo;dark&rdquo;</a> but rather a vital <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-part-2b">building block</a> of western culture — which means that we cannot simply abandon the period to white supremacists. Additionally, on <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-and-race">Monday</a> I sketched out the problems with the idea that the middle ages were racially homogenous, problems that relate both to the historical facts and to our projection of post-Enlightenment race onto the medieval period. Today, I conclude with one of the thornier events of the middle ages: the crusades.</p>

<p>Alt-right movements both in America and in Europe tend to be anti-Islam, using images and phrases (like <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-scotland-glasgow-west-38353706">deus vult</a>) from the medieval crusades to underscore a commitment to protecting western culture from outside threats. The only problem with this is the fact that the medieval crusades weren&rsquo;t about protecting Europe from outside threats.</p>

<p>It will be helpful to start with a brief timeline of the rise of Islam and the crusades. Muhammad, whose visions in the early 7th century became the Qu'ran, founded a religious community that quickly united the tribes of the Arabian peninsula. Neither the Byzantine Empire to the north and west or the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sasanian_Empire">Sasanian Empire</a> to the east had ever had much interest in controlling the arid Arabian peninsula, so Muhammad and his successors filled a power vacuum in the area and quickly began to expand. In the first 150 years of Islam, Arabic tribes conquered across North Africa, into Europe in the Iberian peninsula (modern-day Spain and Portugal), to the east in the old Persian empire, and northward into the Byzantine empire.</p>

<p>As rapidly as the Arabic empire spread, it did not make it into western Europe beyond the Iberian peninsula and the island of Sicily. In the late eighth century, Umayyad incursions into modern-day France were decisively rebuffed by French rulers. After this point, Muslim rulers controlled most of the Iberian peninsula (which they named Al-Andalus) but no longer attempted to invade western Europe across the Pyrenees. And while the history of medieval Spain could be an entire post, it&rsquo;s worth noting that even as Christians reclaimed parts of Spain the Christian/Muslim divide was seldom clear or simplistic. Often Christian rulers warred against their Muslim neighbors, but just as often they allied with Muslim rulers to fight a common enemy — Christian or Muslim. In other words, the narrative of Muslim conquest and Christian resistance does not match the more complicated reality in medieval Spain.</p>

<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Cordoba.jpg" alt="Cordoba cathedral" />
<figcaption>Cathedral in Córdoba, Spain; originally built as a mosque in the late 8th century | © 2015 Berthold Werner | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Spain_Andalusia_Cordoba_BW_2015-10-27_13-54-14.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en">CC BY-SA 3.0</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>The island of Sicily, off the toe of the boot of the Italian peninsula, was also controlled at least partially by Muslim rulers for about 250 years between the ninth and eleventh centuries. Because of its desirable position for trade across the Mediterranean, Sicily has been controlled by most of the key players in the region at one point or another; in the medieval period, it was held by the Goths, then the Byzantines, then Muslim rulers, then the Norman French before becoming a point of contention between the pope, the Holy Roman emperors, and Spanish rulers. In other words, Arabic rulers were one of a multitude of people groups who sought to control the island and its trade — and for Muslim rulers, Sicily was not a launching point for European invasion but a key shipping location in the busy commercial world of the Mediterranean.</p>

<p>In short, after the eighth century the Latin west — the old western part of the Roman empire — was not under serious threat of invasion and conquest by Arabic Muslims.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> However, the old eastern half of the Roman empire, now known as the Byzantine empire, saw a different situation. Because it bordered the Arabian peninsula and in the early middle ages controlled trade routes in what we call the Middle East, the Byzantine empire experienced frequent conflict with the expanding Arabic empire. Over the centuries of the middle ages, the Byzantine world contracted under the initial Arabic expansion, then expanded under two centuries of strong rulers, then contracted again, slowly, until it was overtaken by the Ottoman Turks in 1455.</p>

<p>So in the late eleventh century, on the eve of the crusades, it was the Byzantine empire rather than the Latin west that faced Arabic invaders. The Byzantine period of expansion and strong rulers had come to an end and, in the chaos, Arabic rulers attempted to expand into Byzantium.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Emissaries from Alexios I, the Byzantine emperor, came to pope Urban II in 1095 to ask for help defending the city of Constantinople. Urban II seized on this opportunity and, on November 27, 1095 he promulgated the first crusade in a <a href="https://sourcebooks.fordham.edu/halsall/source/urban2-5vers.html">famous speech.</a></p>

<p>However, Urban II and Alexios I had significantly different visions of what form western aid to the Byzantines should take. Alexios I wanted soldiers, who he would pay; the Byzantine armies like modern armies worked on a payment model. However, western European armies were feudal and land ownership was the foundation of wealth; soldiers were either rewarded with plunder from victories or, for the nobility, granted land for service. Cash payment would not appeal to the nobles who led the armies who fought for land. Alexios I would not have given his land to western European nobles. Urban II not only knew this, but was also deeply concerned about the violent squabbling between Christian rulers over arable land — most of which had been claimed by the late eleventh century.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>Thus, rather than calling for volunteers to defend Constantinople as Alexios I had requested, Urban II called for soldiers to conquer the Holy Land. He thus addresses, in some way, the problem of Arabic incursions into Byzantium while also giving the nobility of Europe a new opportunity to gain territory without fighting against other Christians. It&rsquo;s certainly overly simplistic to see only mercenary reasons for the crusades, since the idea of regaining the Holy Land from the Muslims held significant emotional power as well. But under Urban II&rsquo;s vision of the crusades, most crusaders had a variety of motives for taking part: defeating Muslims, having knightly adventures, gaining land and treasure, earning a <a href="http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07783a.htm">plenary indulgence</a> for sins.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also possible that Urban II hoped to reunite the western church and the eastern church, which had diverged in language, theology and hierarchy as the Roman empire dissolved in the west but only formally split in 1054 CE, recent history for Urban II. However, despite the first hundred years of largely successful crusading, the crusades ended up deepening divisions between the Byzantine empire and the west. The fourth crusade (1202-4) never even reached the Holy Land; instead, after becoming embroiled in political unrest in Constantinople, the unpaid western armies grew restless and plundered the city.</p>

<p>All of which to say: while the initial impetus for the crusades is the request from Byzantium for aid against Muslim invaders, the crusades were only partially, if at all, about defending Europe from the Muslims. In fact, shifting the objective of the first crusade from helping Constantinople to retaking the Holy Land suggests that western rulers weren&rsquo;t particularly concerned about either the fate of Constantinople or keeping Byzantium as a buffer between western Europe and the Arabic empire. Were crusaders motived by the desire to defend Christendom against Muslims? Probably many were. But they also wanted to <em>reclaim</em> or <em>expand</em> Christendom, and few would have seem themselves or their kingdoms as directly threatened by Muslims.</p>

<p>Moreover, remember that identity categories in the middle ages, as I discussed on Monday, could be fluid, complicating European views of Islam. Most western Europeans identified as Christian, a powerful pan-European identity that also linked western and Byzantine Christians. One could not, obviously, identify as both a Christian and a Muslim, and there are plentiful works of art and literature that sharply contrast Christian and Muslim. The twelfth-century <a href="https://sourcebooks.fordham.edu/basis/roland-ohag.asp"><em>Song of Roland</em></a>, for example, presents Muslims as completely evil and worshipping an unholy trinity made up of Mohammed, a demon named Termagant, and the Roman god Apollo. And when king Arthur&rsquo;s rebellious nephew/incestuous son Mordred (very ahistorically) allies with Saracens (a medieval term for Muslims), this proves the depth of Mordred&rsquo;s wickedness.</p>

<p><figure class="float-left">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Saladin.jpg" alt="Saladin" />
<figcaption>Saladin, painted by Cristofano dell'Altissimo, c. 1552-68 | public domain | via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Cristofano_dell%27altissimo,_saladino,_ante_1568_-_Serie_Gioviana.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>And yet, European scholars had great respect for Arabic scholarship, particularly medical scholarship and commentaries on Aristotle. The Muslim ruler <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saladin">Saladin</a> was greatly admired by the leaders of the Third Crusade — especially England&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_I_of_England">Richard I</a> — even as their armies battled. And in the fourteenth century, the English travel writer John Mandeville unfavorably compared Christian nobles to Muslims, who he claimed more closely adhered to the ideals of chivalry and morality in general despite their ignorance of Christianity. These examples show that, despite the large religious divide, scholarship and chivalry provided points of contact between the Christian and Muslim worlds.</p>

<p>My goal in today&rsquo;s post has been to sketch the often complex relationship between the kingdoms of western Europe, the Byzantine empire, and the Muslim world. These relationships were not, with some notable exceptions, always peaceful and harmonious. And because religious and ethnic identities were tightly connected, it is accurate in some senses to see a conflict between Christianity and Islam. And yet the crusades also brought about closer contact between western Europe and the Arabic empire, contact that enriched European scholarship and bridged cultural divides.</p>

<p>It is not historically accurate to imagine medieval Europe as united against an encroaching Islamic threat, or as striving to preserve its cultural heritage in the face of outside invaders. This notion overstates a united European identity, exaggerates the threat posed by the Arabic empire, and ignores the peaceful and productive exchanges of scholarship and culture between the Christian west and Islamic east at various times during the middle ages.</p>

<p>The medieval period is not the best model for modern-day relationships between majority Muslim and majority Christian nations. But neither do the middle ages provide proof that Christianity and Islam are incompatible and must remain locked in combat until one or the other disappears.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>There were periodic Arabic raids along the Mediterranean, including in Marseille and coastal cities in Italy. Like the pagan Viking raids from the north, however, these were not attempts at imperial conquest but smash and grab operations. This is not to minimize the destruction and loss of life, but it&rsquo;s important to distinguish between conquest, as happened in the Spanish peninsula, and raiding.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It&rsquo;s worth noting that, in this same period, the Normans (who at the time ruled England and parts of Sicily from their home territories in France) were also seizing territory along the Mediterranean from the Byzantine Empire.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>The movements to end conflict are collectively known as the Peace and Truce of God.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-09-2017-middle-ages-and-race</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-09-2017-middle-ages-and-race</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Were the European Middle Ages Racially Homogenous?</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/st_maurice.jpg" alt="St Maurice" />
<figcaption>Reliquary statue of St. Maurice, 1525-27 (Aschaffenburg, Hofbibliothek, ms. 14, fol. 227v) | public domain | via <a href="http://medievalpoc.tumblr.com/post/62055886918/anonymous-german-artist-saint-maurice-with-shield">People of Color in European Art History</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Last week, we began a series on white supremacy and the middle ages. I started with the notion that the middle ages were the dark ages (<a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-part-2a">here</a> and <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-part-2b">here</a>), since that idea makes it easy to abandon the middle ages to those who would use it to support their agenda of racial or cultural purity. As we discovered, however, the middle ages — far from being dark — play an important role in the development of western culture.</p>

<p>Last week&rsquo;s posts sketch how the middle ages, rather than being dark and ignorant, are instead a vital period in the development of western culture. But this is not a culture that leads inevitably to white supremacy. Today and Wednesday, I develop this argument along two lines: today, I&rsquo;m going to focus on the idea that Europe was racially homogenous in the middle ages; on Wednesday, I discuss the crusades and the idea that Europe was united in opposition to encroaching Islam.</p>

<p>Today&rsquo;s post on race is not going to be comprehensive, because I&rsquo;m not writing a book. I&rsquo;m including links at the bottom of the post for further reading on race and the middle ages for any who are interested — and I&rsquo;m going to plug the Tumblr <a href="http://medievalpoc.tumblr.com">People of Color in European Art History</a> up here as well, since the art curated there is worth thousands of words insisting that people of color did, in fact, exist in medieval Europe.</p>

<p>But before we turn to the middle ages, we need to start with the Enlightenment for a very specific reason: the eighteenth-century Enlightenment is when our modern notion of race emerged, and specifically the notion of whiteness against which all other races were measured (and found lacking). Human beings undoubtedly have noticed, categorized, and assigned value to differences throughout history, but cultures frame those differences in a variety of ways. Our modern framing of race, including our valuation of European whiteness as the standard from which other races diverge, comes not from biology or some vague feature of human nature or even ancient or medieval western culture, but from Enlightenment thinkers.</p>

<p>The Enlightenment scholars, as they studied the past, projected their ideas about race back onto the middle ages, constructing a purely white medieval Europe. And their legacy lingers: even today, and even among specialists who should know better, the focus is almost always on white figures. You can&rsquo;t get through a graduate degree with a medieval specialty without studying Thomas Aquinas or Dante — but you can (as I know from experience) get said degree without any study of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maimonides">medieval Jewish thinkers</a>, or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Maurice">Saint Maurice</a>, or the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Averroes">Islamic scholars</a> of Sicily and Spain.</p>

<p>And this whitewashing of medieval history shows up even in pop culture representations — in the nearly all-white cast of <em>Game of Thrones,</em> for example, or the periodic grumbling about the BBC&rsquo;s colorblind casting policy in shows like <em>Merlin.</em> Or Tolkien&rsquo;s <em>The Lord of the Rings</em>, a very medieval epic in which the only characters of color are barely-mentioned enemies of Gondor and the West.</p>

<p>Given both the contents of textbooks and the representations we see on screen, plus the assumption that the dark ages must have been ignorant and bigoted, it&rsquo;s no surprise that we assume that the middle ages were racially homogenous. But we should reexamine this assumption through two different lenses: first, the way that medieval people themselves thought about race; and second, the extent to which we can see homogeneity.</p>

<p>The first question is the most complex: how did medieval people think about race? The first thing to know is that Latin, the language of medieval scholarship, doesn&rsquo;t have a term that easily equates to what we mean by &ldquo;race&rdquo; today. Writers could use a few terms, such as <em>gens</em> — a word that can be most broadly translated &ldquo;people,&rdquo; but that can mean &ldquo;nationality&rdquo; or &ldquo;tribe&rdquo; with connotations of biological descent.</p>

<p><figure class="float-left">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/berry_exaltation.jpg" alt="Berry exaltation" />
<figcaption>Exaltation of the Holy Cross from Très Riches Heures du duc de Berry, fol. 193r (Netherlands, c. 1411) | public domain | via <a href="http://medievalpoc.tumblr.com/post/75074878050/hermann-de-limbourg-très-riches-heures-du-duc-de">People of Color in European Art History</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>As Christians, however, medieval European thinkers emphasized common descent from Adam. They also saw the natural environment as an important factor in creating different appearances, which means that physical appearance isn&rsquo;t always tied to race or biological descent. For example, because they believed that extreme heat causes the skin to darken, medieval thinkers thought that an African who relocated to Europe would become lighter-skinned, or see lighter-skinned descendants (the opposite would also be true — fair-skinned Europeans would darken in equatorial climates). From our modern point of view, this significantly misunderstands genetics. But it&rsquo;s also crucial to understand that the physical markers of modern-day race, like skin tone, were not seen by medieval people as barriers to assimilation into other cultures or as indications of character or mental ability.</p>

<p>Additionally, customs, language, and law were viewed by medieval people as key markers of racial or ethnic identity —  social, not biological, factors. Different language groups, what we might call different racial or ethnic groups, frequently coexisted within larger political entities, such as the various princedoms of the Holy Roman Empire or the Welsh and Scots in England. This means that many medieval people would have had complex and overlapping racial and ethnic identities.</p>

<p>These medieval thoughts about race and ethnicity demonstrate that, in the middle ages, &ldquo;race&rdquo; meant something rather different than it does today. And importantly, the idea of racial purity would probably not have made sense to medieval thinkers, since for them race and ethnicity are shaped by natural and social environments — change those, and ethnic identity can also change. One example is the <a href="https://theconversation.com/vikings-were-never-the-pure-bred-master-race-white-supremacists-like-to-portray-84455">Viking</a> settlement of Normandy (in modern-day France). Viking invasions along the Seine turned into settlements, and over time the Viking settlers intermarried with the original inhabitants and adopted the French language and French customs. Neither the Vikings nor the French seem to have been particularly concerned about racial purity or mixed ethnicities, despite facing the inevitable tensions that can arise when two different people groups begin to live together.</p>

<p>So for medieval people, race or ethnicity depended in part on descent, in part on geography, and in part on language, law and customs — a rather more complex and flexible definition of race or ethnicity than what arose in the Enlightenment.</p>

<p>But despite this medieval understanding of race, weren&rsquo;t the vast majority of people in Europe at the time just white?</p>

<p>Hopefully the discussion above has shown that medieval people wouldn&rsquo;t have viewed everyone in Europe as a homogenous race, given a diversity of climates, languages, laws and customs. Some homogenizing factors did, however, exist in Europe. Christianity is the crucial cultural unifier, which I will discuss more on Wednesday with the crusades. For the nobility, the laws of chivalry provided a pan-European identity,<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and the cultural explosion of the twelfth century saw certain styles of art and manuscript production (which we now call Gothic) spread across Europe and supplant more localized styles. But while these factors provided points of contact among European people groups, they did not produce a unified European ethnic identity.</p>

<p>Moreover, Europe had non-white inhabitants. In the Roman period, the Roman custom was to distribute armies across the empire — so North Africans served in England, Gauls in the middle east, etc. As Roman power waned, some of these soldiers undoubtedly remained where they were stationed, becoming absorbed into the population.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Jewish settlements also existed in many cities across Europe, with Jewish people living and working alongside their Christian neighbors but holding distinct languages, laws and customs. Similarly, both Sicily and Spain had Muslim communities that often existed alongside Christian and Jewish communities.</p>

<p>Additionally, Europeans traded with the known world: the Silk Road took merchants to the far east, spices and fables of a Christian kingdom came from India, and artistic influence flowed between southern Europe and west Africa. Travelers like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Polo">Marco Polo</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Mandeville">John Mandeville</a> entertained audiences with tales of their travels — real travels, although highly embellished narratives. In the realm of fiction, foreign knights served in Arthur&rsquo;s fabled court: like the Saracen (Arabic) knight Palomides, a paragon of chivalry who only converts to Christianity as he dies, or the African <a href="http://www.ancienttexts.org/library/celtic/ctexts/morien.html">Sir Morian</a>, hero of his own Dutch romance.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mean to suggest that medieval Europeans valued diversity in a modern sense; that also recreates medieval Europe into our own image. But to imagine Europe in the middle ages as racially homogenous requires us to both ignore evidence to the contrary and to project Enlightenment ideas about race onto medieval people. And while medieval people were certainly quite capable of bigotry, their ideas and experiences of race certainly do not support the notion that medieval Europe is a model for white supremacy or white nationalism.</p>

<p><strong>For further reading:</strong></p>

<p>TEAMS (Teaching Association for Medieval Studies) put together comprehensive guide to resources on the middle ages and race <a href="https://teams-medieval.org/?page_id=76">here</a>.</p>

<p>The Public Medievalist Special Series: <a href="https://www.publicmedievalist.com/race-racism-middle-ages-toc/">Race, Racism and the Middle Ages</a></p>

<p><a href="http://medievalpoc.tumblr.com">People of Color in European Art History</a>, a Tumblr with many images of people of color in European art.</p>

<p>Robert Bartlett, &ldquo;Medieval and Modern Concepts of Race and Ethnicity,&rdquo; <em>Journal of Medieval and Early Modern Studies</em> 31.1 (2001), 39-56. PDF <a href="http://npproseminar.pbworks.com/f/Bartlett,+Medieval+Race.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Note that this identity is linked to social status, uniting the European nobility while strongly distinguishing them from the lower classes — so chivalry can&rsquo;t function as the foundation for a European identity for all.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Historian [Mary Beard][8] endured extensive harassment on Twitter this summer for affirming the fact that black Roman soldiers served in England.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-06-2017-middle-ages-part-2b</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-06-2017-middle-ages-part-2b</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 09:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>The Middle Ages were the Dark Ages and Everything was Awful All. The. Time. (Part B)</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Chartres_rose_window.jpg" alt="Chartres Rose Window" />
<figcaption>Rose Window, Chartres Cathedral 1194-1220 | photo by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Eusebius">Eusebius</a> | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Chartres_-_cathédrale_-_rosace_nord.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></p>

<p></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>We&rsquo;re focusing this week on the idea of the middle ages as &ldquo;dark ages&rdquo; because this common narrative, although lacking historical support, makes us inclined to believe that the middle ages were a period of ignorance, barbarism, superstition and bigotry. So when white supremacists use the middle ages to support their claims that western culture is white (and, often, Christian), popular ideas of the middle ages do nothing to combat this view. I&rsquo;ll turn next week to the specific arguments about cultural homogeneity and the crusades, but this week I am laying a foundation for understanding the middle ages as culturally vibrant and crucial in the development of western culture — but a western culture that does not inevitably support white supremacy.</p>

<p>On <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-part-2a">Wednesday,</a> I sketched out my first objection to the &ldquo;dark ages&rdquo; narrative, namely that Rome fell to uncivilized barbarians and everything was basically awful until the Renaissance, when light returned to Europe. Today I look at the other two aspects of the dark ages narrative, that Roman culture disappeared and that the middle ages produced little to nothing of value for western culture.</p>

<p>Although the continuation of Roman culture isn&rsquo;t obvious because of the popular narrative, it really should be obvious. Christianity, the official religion of Rome from the late fourth century onward, continued to be the dominant religion as the various people groups in Europe converted (some more and some less voluntarily) to Christianity. Latin continued to be spoken, although without the standardizing influence of imperial structures it gradually diverged into what we call romance languages — French, Spanish, Romanian, Portuguese, etc. But as the vernacular (commonly spoken) dialects diverged, Latin remained the standard language of communication across Europe for both the Church and scholarship more broadly.</p>

<p>Roman authors were preserved and studied; educated people from the early to the late middle ages would have been familiar with Ovid, Virgil, Cicero, and a whole host of Roman writers — not to mention the Latin church fathers like Jerome and Augustine.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mean to discount cultural change, or the impact of the power shifts as the Roman empire disintegrated. The period from the late fifth century through the eighth centuries was marked by invasions and shifting political alliances accompanied by the deterioration of Roman infrastructure (primarily roads and trade routes). The meant less trade and economic prosperity, and as the influence of Rome decreased Germanic customs and laws became more prominent (we can still see their influence in English and American law, in things like juries).</p>

<p>But even as they were aware of their Germanic heritage, most rulers in medieval Europe admired Rome and viewed it as also part of their heritage. Just one example will make my point: the emperor Charlemagne. He was crowned Holy Roman Emperor in 800 CE. The joke goes that the political entity called the Holy Roman Empire was neither holy, nor Roman, nor an empire — and there&rsquo;s some truth in that. But Charlemagne aspired to rule in the style of Rome, and he reopened trade routes, communicated with the Byzantine emperor, and sponsored schools and scholars in what researchers today call the Carolingian renaissance. It&rsquo;s easy to see from our vantage point the differences between Charlemagne&rsquo;s kingdom and the Roman empire. But his desire to emulate the Roman emperors of old should tell us that Rome continued to have an effect on medieval culture.</p>

<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Aachen.jpg" alt="Aachen" />
<figcaption>Aachen Cathedral, constructed under Charlemagne beginning c. 796 CE | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Aachener_dom_oktagon.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0">CC BY-SA 3.0</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>So why the idea that culture was lost? First, there&rsquo;s that barbarian narrative, promoted by Roman writers during the empire and by historians of Rome since the Italian renaissance. Barbarians are the opposite of cultured — in fact, they smash culture. But this ignores reality, as I discuss above, and ignores the fact that these &ldquo;barbarians&rdquo; also had a culture that may have been different from Roman culture but was not inferior. And as with other cultural absorptions before this (as when the Romans emulated Greek culture), western culture became a blend of Greco-Roman, Judeo-Christian, and Germanic cultures.</p>

<p>But the grain of truth in the &ldquo;lost culture&rdquo; is the loss of Greek in the medieval west. Some scholars in the middle ages almost certainly learned Greek (<a href="%20https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/abelard/">Peter Abelard</a> and possible even <a href="%20https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A9lo%C3%AFse">Heloise</a> are examples), but they were a distinct minority. Because very few works by prominent Greek thinkers had been translated into Latin, with the exception of Plato, much Greek philosophy and literature vanished from western Europe until the twelfth century renaissance, when the works of Aristotle were translated into Latin (via Arabic scholarship) and the medieval academic world was transformed.</p>

<p>The scholars of the Italian renaissance, beginning in the fourteenth century, rediscovered more and more Greek texts and began to actually learn Greek, unlike most university scholars of the twelfth century. This does, once again, change the academy with new ideas; but it&rsquo;s a vast overstatement to imagine that this is a rediscovery of western culture. It&rsquo;s a rediscovery of some aspects of Greek culture and a shift in how those sources are studied — even if the Italian humanists paint themselves in a far more radical light.</p>

<p>Finally — and I imagine that I&rsquo;ve partially made this point already — the middle ages were a culturally rich period. The idea that historians have few records would be laughable it it weren&rsquo;t so common. True, there are certain periods and places where historical records are fragmentary; invasions in the fifth through seventh centuries by Germanic tribes and, later, Arabic groups disrupt or destroy records, as do the ninth and tenth century invasions by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magyar_tribes">Magyars</a> and Vikings. And obviously, cultural productions (art, literature, scholarship) are difficult during periods when people are focused on simple survival.</p>

<p>But the cultural accomplishments of the middle ages are substantial. Medieval buildings still dot the European landscape. Medieval authors, like Chaucer and Dante, shaped the course of western literature by writing in vernacular languages rather than Latin. Medieval artists and artisans pioneered stained glass and built soaring cathedrals that we still admire. Many of the great universities of Europe — Oxford, Paris, Bologna — were all established in the high middle ages. Scholasticism grappled with how to integrate theology and philosophy, faith and reason, in ways that still shape our approaches to those topics. <a href="http://d.lib.rochester.edu/teams/text/staley-book-of-margery-kempe-introduction">Margery Kempe</a>, in England, wrote what many consider the first autobiography, while French and English writers pioneered the prose narratives that became the modern novel. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double-entry_bookkeeping_system#History">Double entry bookkeeping</a> was invented in medieval Italy while Italian city-states like Florence embraced republican forms of government. The nation-state itself as a political entity emerged in the late middle ages.</p>

<p>I could go on, but you get the picture.</p>

<p>Was there oppression and injustice in medieval Europe? Certainly. There were also odd notions about bathing, and medical care — while based on Greek and Roman ideas — was not particularly effective.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> As in most of the ancient world, illiterate peasants<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> made up the vast majority of the population while a small cadre of nobles held the wealth and power.</p>

<p>But to dismiss the middle ages as the dark ages, a time of ignorance and barbarity, is to ignore a vast swath of time and its equally vast influence on the development of western culture.</p>

<p>If we can&rsquo;t simply dismiss the middle ages as ignorant and backwards, then we also can&rsquo;t abandon it to those who would twist history to support white supremacy. And in parts three and four of this series, I will turn to two main arguments for white supremacy in the middle ages and examine why they are wrong.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Medical care remained based in Greek [humoral theory][7] far beyond the middle ages, however.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Literacy rates are notoriously difficult to measure. If literacy meant knowledge of Latin — how medieval people would have measured literacy — only a small portion of the population was literate. Literacy numbers expand if we include vernacular literacy, and expand further if we consider very basic measures like the ability to sign one&rsquo;s name.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-part-2a</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-04-2017-middle-ages-part-2a</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 09:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>The Middle Ages were the Dark Ages and Everything was Awful All. The. Time. (Part A)</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Fall_Rome.jpg" alt="Fall of Rome" />
<figcaption>Thomas Cole, <i>Destruction</i> from <i>The Course of Empire</i>, 1836 | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Cole_Thomas_The_Course_of_Empire_Destruction_1836.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Welcome to part 2 of my series on the middle ages and why they matter!  As Christians who oppose white supremacy we should take seriously the attempt by white supremacists to frame the middle ages as a racially homogenous (white) Christian utopia. Imagining the past in this way allows white supremacists to believe that western culture (or, more precisely, white culture) is under siege by (take your pick) multiculturalism, feminism, Islam, or political correctness. I introduced this idea in <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-02-2017-middle-ages-introduction">part 1</a>; in part 3 I will look more closely at the claim that Europe was racially homogenous, and in part 4 I will turn to the Crusades.</p>

<p>For part 2, I&rsquo;m starting with the characterization of the medieval period in Europe (roughly 500 - 1500 CE) as the &ldquo;dark ages.&rdquo; This misconception about the middle ages allows us to ignore it. We&rsquo;re predisposed to believe that medieval people were ignorant and racist, so even if we reject the <em>purpose</em> of the white supremacist argument (to elevate whiteness), popular understandings of the middle ages give us no reason to dispute the <em>data</em> behind the claims.</p>

<p>I want to make a case for disputing the data, so we can not only reject the conclusions of white supremacy but also its facts. So we&rsquo;re starting with the idea that the middle ages were the Dark Ages. I cringe just typing the phrase, but you know the narrative: Rome was awesome and cultured (or, at least, powerful). Then stinking, uncivilized barbarians invaded and destroyed. The End. Dark ages for a millennium until the scholars of the Italian Renaissance rediscovered truth and beauty and science and all that. (And, bonus for Protestants, the Reformers simultaneously &ldquo;rediscovered&rdquo; Christianity.)</p>

<p>This narrative crops up everywhere, even amongst the most educated people. For example, an otherwise solid book published in 2017 (I reviewed it <a href="https://www.cbeinternational.org/resources/review/book-review-gender-roles-and-people-god">here</a>), says this about the middle ages:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Rome&rsquo;s days were numbered, and by the end of the fifth century, the Ostrogothic Kingdom rose from the ruins of the Western Roman Empire. The thousand-year "Dark Ages&rdquo; had begun, so called because historians have few records from that long period in which much of the earlier culture was lost. In its heyday, the Roman Empire had provided widespread literacy, law, historical records, and an international language of science and literature. But invading barbaric tribes had no interest in preserving much of Roman culture.&ldquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p></blockquote>

<p>This nonsense was written by a scholar with advanced degrees and passed through the editing process at a reputable publisher, showing how deeply ingrained this narrative is.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to break this quote down and address three specific misconceptions that undergird the idea of the &ldquo;dark ages&rdquo;: first, that Rome experienced some sort of dramatic fall; second, that Roman (and thus western) culture was lost; and third, that we have few records (historical or otherwise) from this period.</p>

<p>First, the fall of Rome. It&rsquo;s common knowledge that Rome fell to invading barbarian tribes.</p>

<p>But the reality is not anywhere near so simple, even though it is a fact that from 476 CE onward (with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justinian_I">brief exception</a>), the western portion of the Roman empire was no longer ruled by people who were ethnically Roman. That &ldquo;ethnically Roman&rdquo; is key, as is the division between eastern and western halves of the empire.</p>

<p>In 293 CE, the emperor Diocletian instituted a tetrarchy, a system of four rulers in the Roman empire. Although his tetrarchy didn&rsquo;t last for long, this system recognized the deep-seated cultural, linguistic and economic divisions between the eastern and western halves of the empire, and a two-emperor system became the new normal. Two hundred years later, Gothic leaders sought to rule in the west, but not the east; and the eastern Roman Empire continued to thrive — as what we call the Byzantine Empire — until 1455.</p>

<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Roman_Empire.jpg" alt="Roman Empire" />
<figcaption>Roman Empire in 460; different colors show the two halves of the empire | Tataryn77 via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3ARoman_Empire_460_AD.png">via Wikimedia Commons</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0">CC BY-SA 3.0</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>The Gothic rulers of Rome came, of course, from Germanic tribes, but by the time they ruled Rome in the fifth century they were quite Romanized. They were Christians, they used Latin, they served in Rome&rsquo;s armies as soldiers and generals, they held titles bestowed by the eastern emperor and the Roman Senate. This Romanization of some Gothic tribes began in the fourth century, when several Germanic tribes had been given land and partially incorporated into the Roman Empire in order to defend the empire against other tribes.</p>

<p>Rome, however, treated these tribes (called federated tribes) very poorly, giving them land that couldn&rsquo;t be farmed and withholding promised rights. This understandably angered many Germanic leaders — but they also understood that the Roman army was an excellent way to advance in power and influence. Alaric, the Visigoth who sacked Rome in 410, was a Roman general. Odoacer, the Ostrogoth who took control of the city of Rome in 476 (the date traditionally assigned to the Fall of Rome), was also a Roman soldier who enjoyed the support of the Roman senate and who, in theory at least, placed himself under the authority of the emperor in the east.</p>

<p>But by the time that these Gothic rulers took control of the western part of the empire, Roman control in western Europe had already diminished significantly. Roman armies had conquered large swaths of Europe, building roads and aqueducts and towns for soldiers and bureaucrats, but the expense of maintaining the infrastructure of empire far outweighed the income that came from these western territories. From the mid-third century on, Rome had struggled to maintain the poorer western half of the empire as its center of power shifted eastward. So the Gothic kings styled themselves as Romans in many ways, but their power, like the power of the Roman rulers they replaced, certainly never equalled the power of the emperors during the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pax_Romana"><em>Pax Romana</em></a> (which ended in the late second century).</p>

<p>Additionally, while many Gothic tribes were Romanized, their rulers tended to think in terms of kin groups rather than empires. Thus the power of the Roman rulers gradually diminished to the Italian peninsula itself while other Germanic groups — some Romanized, some not — ruled in various parts of Europe in the early middle ages.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve very briefly sketched complex history, but it should be clear that the reports of Rome&rsquo;s death are greatly exaggerated. The Roman empire in the west gradually diminished for economic and political reasons for at least a century before the event we call the fall of Rome in 476 CE. Moreover, the Gothic rulers who took over the western part of the empire were Romanized, as their interest in gaining the support of the Roman Senate and the blessings of the eastern emperor shows. This doesn&rsquo;t mean that things stayed the same; the western empire slowly dissolved as a political entity. But the barbarian hordes narrative certainly doesn&rsquo;t hold up to scrutiny.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve spent a long time on this first point about the fall of Rome because it&rsquo;s necessary for the second point: that Roman culture did not disappear. I&rsquo;ll turn to my other two points, that Roman culture continued and that the middle ages are a rich source of history and culture, on Friday.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Alice Matthews, <em>Gender Roles and the People of God</em> (Grand Rapids, MI: Zondervan, 2017), p. 171.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-02-2017-middle-ages-introduction</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/10/10-02-2017-middle-ages-introduction</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 08:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>The Middle Ages and White Supremacy: An Introduction</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/LindisfarneFol27rIncipitMatt.jpg" alt="Lindisfarne Matthew" />
<figcaption>Lindisfarne Gospels, folio 27r (beginning of the Gospel of Matthew), 8th c. | public domain | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3ALindisfarneFol27rIncipitMatt.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Last week, I wrote about how the culture war is concerned, at least in part, with defending and defining western culture. The &ldquo;defining&rdquo; piece is crucial: western culture has been around for at least 2500 years, and that&rsquo;s if we only start with the Greeks (the Golden Age of Athens began in roughly 480 BCE). Western culture has also spread geographically from a small section of the Mediterranean (again, if we discount the earlier Fertile Crescent cultures) to dominate two continents and influence most of the rest of the globe.</p>

<p>Obviously, something that old and that spread out contains multitudes.</p>

<p>In order to make this history more manageable, most people intentionally or not focus on western history post-Renaissance or post-Enlightenment. (That is, western history after 1500 or 1700 CE.) Scholars designate this the &ldquo;modern&rdquo; period, and this is an age of rationalism, science and technology, individualism, capitalism, colonialism, and democracy.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also distressingly common for people — laypeople and scholars alike — to accept the assertions of Renaissance and Enlightenment thinkers that they emerged from a previous period of darkness and chaos. &ldquo;Renaissance&rdquo; means rebirth; &ldquo;enlightenment&rdquo; emphasizes the light (of reason) triumphing over darkness.</p>

<p>These are inspiring narratives, no doubt, and they fit neatly into our own current sense of being the best, the most advanced, the most intelligent society in the history of earth. But in addition to a wee bit of hubris, these claims actually obscure a far richer and more complex understanding of western culture.</p>

<p>So, why does this matter? Why should a modern-day Christian living in the western world care about understanding the past?</p>

<p>There are a lot of possible answers to that question. If we don&rsquo;t understand the past, we are doomed to repeat it. Or, understanding the past makes us better, well-rounded people. Or, understanding the past gives us new perspectives on the problems of modern life.</p>

<p>All of these are true, at least in part (although I have Things To Say about the &ldquo;doomed to repeat the past&rdquo; bit). But there&rsquo;s a more pressing reason to understand the pre-Enlightenment, pre-Renaissance past these days, and that&rsquo;s thanks to the growing visibility of white supremacy.</p>

<p>As <a href="http://www.inthemedievalmiddle.com/2017/08/teaching-medieval-studies-in-time-of.html?m=1">many</a> <a href="https://psmag.com/education/nazis-love-taylor-swift-and-also-the-crusades">medievalists</a> (scholars of the middle ages) have recently pointed out, those of us with expertise in the field need to do a better job of explaining how the medieval past does not support white supremacy. If we as Christians also want to reject white supremacy, it&rsquo;s worth understanding and resisting how this movement twists medieval history.</p>

<p>And as Christians, this task is <em>especially</em> important because the way that white supremacists frame the middle ages is often as an era of the church militant and triumphant: it&rsquo;s not a coincidence that pictures of the rally in Charlottesville this August show men with medieval shields and crusader crosses, often paired with the Latin phrase <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deus_vult"><em>deus vult</em></a> — a crusading slogan.</p>

<p>If we care about racism, history, or Christianity, we should care about understanding the medieval past and the role of the church in that past.</p>

<p>(Note: for simplicity, I will use &ldquo;middle ages&rdquo; and &ldquo;medieval&rdquo; to refer to the European middle ages. But the world didn&rsquo;t contract to Europe in this period: a variety of cultures flourished in the far east, the middle east, the Indian subcontinent, Africa, and the Americas — and Europe had contact with many of them. Focusing only on Europe is, of course, one way in which the primacy of western culture is reinforced. But my own expertise is in the European middle ages, and this is the specific era that is being twisted to support white nationalism.)</p>

<p>Over the next two weeks, I will examine a couple of specific misconceptions about the middle ages that fuel the myths of white supremacy:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>The middle ages were the Dark Ages and Everything was Awful All. The. Time.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Europe was racially homogenous.</strong></li>
<li><strong>The crusades were about defending Europe from Islam.</strong></li>
</ol>


<p>I hope that, through the next several posts, I can show that the history and culture of the middle ages in Europe cannot be used a support for white supremacy. I want to replace the myth of racial, cultural and religious homogeneity with a more complex picture of medieval history.</p>

<p>Now, I&rsquo;m going to be completely honest here: I love the middle ages. I find them fascinating on so many levels: the theological debates, the literary innovations, the emergence of the nation-state, the art, the manuscripts. Basically everything. I&rsquo;ve also spent the last fifteen or so years of my life studying this period and helping my students to understand it.</p>

<p>So I&rsquo;m a little passionate.</p>

<p>Like all other time periods (and maybe more so, since the medieval period spans roughly a thousand years), there are good and bad parts. And I&rsquo;m certainly not interested in the slightest in giving up my voting rights, sweat-wicking fabrics, antibiotics or Netflix. All of which to say: I&rsquo;m not interested in glorifying chivalry or monarchy, or sugar-coating the really sucky aspects of living in the middle ages.</p>

<p>But this is also part of our history, and as we think about what it might mean to move beyond modernism, understanding the pre-modern past can be instructive. And now, more than ever, we must assert and affirm that western culture does not inevitably lead to white supremacy (although it has produced plenty of white supremacists).</p>

<p>Come with me over the next two weeks to learn a little more about the strange and wonderful world of the middle ages as we reclaim the history of Europe.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-29-2017-apocalyptic-fiction</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-29-2017-apocalyptic-fiction</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Apocalyptic Fiction</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Durer_horsemen.jpg" alt="Durer Apocalypse" />
<figcaption>Albrecht Dürer, <i>The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse,</i> c. 1497-98 | image via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Four_Horsemen_of_the_Apocalypse_by_Dürer.png">Wikimedia commons</a></figcaption></p>

<p></figure></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a fan of science fiction and fantasy — have been since my dad started reading me <em>The Hobbit</em> when I was six or seven. Early exposure to Tolkien and C.S. Lewis likely predisposed me to medieval studies and set up a lifelong skepticism of realistic fiction.</p>

<p>While I enjoy SF/F of all types, I&rsquo;m always particularly intrigued by how writers integrate faith into their worlds. Charlie Stross&rsquo;s series <em>The Laundry Files</em> doesn&rsquo;t portray faith (especially of the American evangelical variety) particularly positively. But the series focuses on a coming apocalypse in which Lovecraftian horrors from beyond our universe will crash into our reality and devour us all, and I find this vision of the coming apocalypse both horrifying and compelling — the mark of enjoyable fiction.</p>

<p>I confess that apocalyptic and post-apocalyptic fiction always piques my interest. Maybe it comes of having been raised <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dispensationalism">dispensationalist</a> — you can take the girl out of the pre-trib rapture, but you can&rsquo;t take the four horsemen of the apocalypse out of the girl (as they say).</p>

<p>Stross&rsquo;s novels mostly follow Bob Howard, programmer and British civil servant, as he attempts to avert apocalyptic events. The series was described to me as James Bond meets Cthulhu, but only if James Bond is a nerd who constantly ends up way over his head and who actually, like, respects women (although he still has cool gadgets). Oh, and Bob works for a shadowy British agency dedicated to helping humanity survive <strong><em>Code Nightmare Green</em></strong>, a rapidly approaching time when our reality will coincide with the reality of those Lovecraftian horrors who will most likely find humanity an appetizing snack.</p>

<p><figure class="float-left">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Atrocity_Achives.jpg" alt="Atrocity Archives" />
<figcaption>Cover art by Steve Montiglio | image via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Atrocity_Archives-Charles_Stross_(2004).jpg">Wikipedia</a></figcaption></p>

<p></figure></p>

<p>Stross does a fantastic job of capturing the pure horror of the vastly powerful non-human entities that are just waiting for a chance to come to earth and consume it. One such entity is simply called the Sleeper: this being is currently trapped in an a pyramid on a dead planet guarded by zombie Russian soldiers, in a bizarre scene custom-designed to produce nightmares.</p>

<p>In <em>The Apocalypse Codex</em>, the fourth book in the series, an American religious group led by the charismatic Ray Schiller seeks to wake the Sleeper. It seems that Schiller truly believes that the Sleeper is Christ and that he, by infecting people with parasitic hosts, is bringing about the Second Coming. Stross does present this cult as a perversion of more normal manifestations of Christianity (i.e., he doesn&rsquo;t suggest that the eucharist actually allows mind-controlling parasites into the bodies of partakers). But by linking the coming Lovecraftian horrors to apocalyptic Christian beliefs, Stross raises an interesting question about the nature of the apocalypse.</p>

<p>As Christians, we typically view the Second Coming of Christ (with or without a rapture or a millennial kingdom) as a good thing, although there may be a few unpleasant moments with beasts and Babylonian women of questionable morals. As N.T. Wright has noted in <em>Surprised by Hope</em>, Christians are often muddled about what life after death or the return of Christ means — but we do tend to agree that it will ultimately be a good thing for at least some of humanity (typically including us, of course).</p>

<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Cthulhu.jpg" alt="Cthulhu" />
<figcaption>H.P. Lovecraft, sketch of Cthulhu, 1934 | image via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Cthulhu_sketch_by_Lovecraft.jpg">Wikipedia</a></figcaption></p>

<p></figure></p>

<p>But think about this from another point of view: the second coming is <em>apocalyptic</em>. Even if we believe, with Wright, that Christ is returning not to annihilate but to to make new, the world will be completely changed. We believe that this change will be for the better, bringing peace and justice and God&rsquo;s good kingdom come on earth. Yet we&rsquo;re still imagining an alien entity coming down and remaking the entire world.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not suggesting that we need to start imagining God as one of Lovecraft&rsquo;s Great Old Ones, inimical to humanity. But we tend to imagine that God&rsquo;s kingdom will conform to our own ideas of happiness and goodness, whether that&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_House_(song)">mansions and football</a>, angels with harps on clouds, or peace on earth and the total eradication of mosquitoes (not just me, right?).</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth remembering that the return of Christ, the establishment of his kingdom on earth, will be a cataclysmic event that upturns the entire order of the created world. This is cause for rejoicing, as all that is wrong is made right again. But it&rsquo;s also a transformation beyond our wildest imaginings. As C.S. Lewis reminds us, our God is good, but he is not safe.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m more than happy to avoid the apocalypse as envisioned by Stross, even if I enjoy stories about British agents battling unspeakable horrors from beyond our universe. But it&rsquo;s worth remembering, now and again, that the transformation we await as Christians will be bigger than we can possibly understand.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-27-2017-culture-war-addendum</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-27-2017-culture-war-addendum</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 08:10:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Culture War Addendum</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/school_of_athens.jpg" alt="School of Athens" />
<figcaption>Raphael, <i>The School of Athens,</i> 1511 | image via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Raphael_School_of_Athens.jpg">Wikimedia commons</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>I want to make a brief addendum to my two culture war posts last week (<a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-18-2017-culture-war-I">here</a> and <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-20-2017-culture-war-II">here</a> if you missed them). In those posts, I looked at how the culture war mentality creates a dichotomy between culture and church that prevents the church from either engaging productively with or acknowledging its dependence on culture.</p>

<p>But today I want to sketch a deeper background to the culture wars. I want to look at the nostalgia, and specifically the nostalgia for a particular version of western culture, that underlies the culture war ideology.</p>

<p>This may seem initially counter-intuitive: isn&rsquo;t the culture war a fight <em>against</em> culture? In some ways, yes; but it&rsquo;s also a fight against how, in the view of some, modern culture has shifted away from the values of traditional western society.</p>

<p>From this point of view, the culture wars aren&rsquo;t about church against culture at all, but about who gets to define and shape (western) culture — with a vision of culture rooted in the (nostalgically imagined) past.</p>

<p>This becomes evident when we consider what the culture wars <em>don&rsquo;t</em> normally attack or even criticize: democracy. Capitalism. Individualism. Rationalism. These are the values of post-Enlightenment western culture, but they certainly aren&rsquo;t expressly biblical values.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>This defense of western culture has two broad results. First, it is the precondition that makes self-examination so difficult for the church. The culture war isn&rsquo;t particularly interested in interrogating the church&rsquo;s relationship to democracy, capitalism, rationalism or individualism, because those are viewed as western values almost equivalent to Christianity itself.</p>

<p>Second, it reinforces the elevation of western culture as the greatest culture. Because Christianity largely developed within western culture, the two become more or less synonymous. And if Christianity is the greatest religion, western culture must (to follow the logic) be the greatest culture.</p>

<p>These are all broad claims that deserve to be teased out in greater detail. But my point here is that the evangelical culture war meshes easily with a slightly different version of the culture war: not an explicitly evangelical or Christian one, but a war to defend western culture against perceived threats (such as multiculturalism, political correctness, feminism — insert a bogeyman <em>du jour</em>).</p>

<p>For the record, I understand why it is difficult to disentangle Christianity from western culture; after all, for the centuries from Constantine onward Christianity has had a significant influence on western culture. And as Christianity becomes a less dominant social force, a sense of crisis and nostalgia is understandable.</p>

<p>But we must be careful that our faithfulness to Christianity is not confused with faithfulness to western culture. Christianity has and will continue to thrive in a variety of cultures, and no culture ever fully aligns with the values of Christianity.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Capitalism didn&rsquo;t exist for the writers of the Old or New Testament. In first-century Rome, democracy was a failed Greek experiment that was rejected by Plato and Aristotle themselves. While western culture has always valued rational thought, Enlightenment rationalism elevates this approach above all other ways of understanding the world. Similarly with individualism: western culture sees pendulum swings between individual and communal focuses, but the Enlightenment elevates the individual.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-25-2017-wonder-Woman-Sin-Jesus</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-25-2017-wonder-Woman-Sin-Jesus</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2017 08:35:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Wonder Woman, Sin, and Jesus</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/wonder_woman_2.jpg" alt="Wonder Woman" />
<figcaption>© 2017 <a href="https://www.warnerbros.com/wonder-woman#expanded">Warner Bros.</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<blockquote><p><em>The line dividing good and evil cuts through the heart of every human being.</em>
<em>— Alexander Solzhenitsyn</em></p></blockquote>

<p><em>Fair warning: here be spoilers</em></p>

<p>Watching <em>Wonder Woman</em> on video last week, for a second time, I was struck by the way the storyline handles the idea of sin and evil in the world. I was also struck by how, even as she grapples with the evil within humanity, Diana chooses to love humanity in a way that reflects Christ.</p>

<p>Of course, having a superhero be a Christ-figure is so common as to be a cliché. Many male superheroes, in at least some of their storylines, fit this trope: Superman (obvs), Batman, Spiderman, Iron Man in <em>The Avengers</em>. Even the B-cast characters can be Christ-figures, like Agent Phil Coulson (<em>The Avengers</em>, <em>Agents of Shield</em>). These characters all sacrifice themselves for the sake of others, and — spoiler alert — none of them stay dead after their sacrifice (if they even die at all).</p>

<p>But Diana isn’t this sort of Christ-figure. She does leave her paradise of a home, and she certainly puts herself in danger for others — but at least in this summer’s film, she does not sacrifice herself for the sake of others. Instead, she chooses to live with humanity, loving them despite their flaws.</p>

<p>As the film sets up this choice, we see that at first Diana’s decision to help humanity is easy. She has been taught that Zeus created humans in his own image; as her mother tells her, mankind is “fair and good, strong and passionate.” But they become corrupted by Ares, god of war, envious of his father’s creation. Despite the intervention of the Amazons, humans remained corrupted, and eventually a war broke out between Ares and the other gods.</p>

<p>When Diana learns that World War I is raging — the Great War, the War to End All Wars — she is convinced that Ares is responsible. She leaves Themyscira, convinced that she can end the war by killing Ares. But what she discovers is more complicated. Ares is involved, yes (this is, after all, a superhero movie). But humans are not simply innocents, corrupted by another. They are fully complicit in the evil that is war.</p>

<p>The film shows the evil of humanity repeatedly. The unwillingness of leaders to seek peace. The stream of wounded humanity as Steve and Diana cross into Europe. The broken spirit of Charlie. The devastation of no man’s land, reflected in bodies, villages and landscapes. The acknowledgment that even though the Americans are fighting against oppression in this war, they conquered and oppressed native populations.</p>

<p>But Diana does not truly face this evil until, when she thinks she has killed Ares, she is shocked that the soldiers continue their destructive work, oblivious to her fight with General Ludendorff. She is experiencing what Ares later confirms: he may give some well-placed nudges towards evil, but humans are capable of great evil on their own.</p>

<p>This realization devastates Diana. Her view of humanity — “fair and good,” in the words of her mother’s bedtime story — is shattered.</p>

<p>But even as she turns to leave, newly aware of the truth in her mother’s parting words that humanity does not deserve her, she sees her companions willing to sacrifice themselves in order to save others. She sees Steve Trevor’s ultimate act of bravery and selflessness.</p>

<p>Diana faces the truth of the Solzhenitsyn quote above: humanity is both evil and good. And rather than abandon humanity in disdain of the evil, she chooses to stay out of love for the good.</p>

<p>Now, the analogy to Christ isn’t perfect. Unlike Diana, Jesus was fully aware of humanity’s sinfulness when he became incarnate. But like Christ, Diana also lives amongst humanity, serving and saving, because of her love for them. She leaves her home on Paradise Island and her place as the daughter of the queen because she believes that people, regardless of their evil nature, deserve a hero, deserve a savior.</p>

<p>This isn’t a side of the Christ-trope that we often see, at least in blockbuster films. When the hero dies, or nearly dies, for others, the focus typically remains on the hero. Sure, we get shots of grateful New Yorkers, but the hero’s bravery is the central point. Diana’s choice isn’t so much bravery as commitment, and the focus shifts from her actions to her reasons for the action, to her love for undeserving humanity.</p>

<p><em>Wonder Woman</em> tells Diana’s origin story. We see this as she learns who she is (the god-killer) and as she embraces her power in the fabulous no-man’s land scene. But the story behind the story is signaled by the photograph she receives as the film begins: the story of how she came to love humanity, the tale of why she chose to stay.</p>

<p>This origin story reminds us of the evil of humanity, of our sin nature. But it also reminds us of the lavish love of Christ, who lived among us despite the evil within each us and who never tells us that we don’t deserve him.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-22-2017-wheaton-football</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-22-2017-wheaton-football</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 09:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Idolizing Success: Wheaton Football Edition</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Blanchard.jpg" alt="Blanchard" />
<figcaption>Blanchard Hall, Wheaton College | © 2010 <a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/43943756@N07">Teemu008</a> | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Blanchard_Hall_(5978664560).jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/deed.en">CC-BY 2.5</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p><em>Note: I&rsquo;m assuming that the charges brought against the five accused players are largely true, especially given that Wheaton did apparently take some disciplinary action. Perhaps there are details that will justify allowing these players to remain on the team following the incident — but given the propensity of both sports teams and Christian organizations to downplay wrongdoing in order to protect their own reputation, I am skeptical that Wheaton&rsquo;s approach was sufficient given the magnitude of the hazing. As an alum, I truly hope that this incident is isolated and that it reminds the college that there are greater things than winning football games.</em></p>

<p>I was going to end this week on a lighter note, with a piece on sin and <em>Wonder Woman</em> (well, somewhat lighter … ). But then <a href="http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/local/breaking/ct-wheaton-college-football-hazing-met-20170918-story.html">news broke</a> about five Wheaton College football players charged with felonies after a hazing incident that took place a year ago. Wheaton is my alma mater, and I&rsquo;m appalled at the details of this incident.</p>

<p>But even more appalling is the fact that all five football players who are accused of assaulting their first-year teammate were still on the team roster as of early this week. According to the Chicago <em>Tribune</em>, Wheaton did hire a third-party investigator and took &ldquo;corrective action,&rdquo; which may have only amounted to community service and an 8-page essay.</p>

<p>Let that sink in: community service and an <em>essay</em> for actions that are resulting in felony charges. (And while the five players have only been charged, not convicted, the fact that Wheaton imposed some disciplinary action indicates to me that the charges have merit.)</p>

<p>A Wheaton spokesperson noted that the actions of these football players are inconsistent with the values of Wheaton, and as an alum I wholeheartedly agree. But if these actions are so far removed from Wheaton&rsquo;s values, why did the players face such minimal consequences? Why were they still allowed on the team?</p>

<p>Alan Jacobs, a former Wheaton and current Baylor professor (who thus knows something about football scandals), <a href="http://blog.ayjay.org/15988/">noted astutely</a> that &ldquo;Collegiate Football Success is the most jealous of gods. It will tolerate the worship of no other deities, and there will be no end to the sacrifices it demands.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I think Jacobs is absolutely right. Even those of us with little interest in sports (like me) cannot help but be aware of the repeated scandals that plague both college and professional athletics. The need to win excuses, and sometimes encourages, bad behavior on the part of players ranging from cheating (on the field or in the classroom) to domestic violence.</p>

<p>Since I don&rsquo;t follow Wheaton football, I have no idea if the five accused players were any good — but I imagine that losing five at a time (plus, of course, the assaulted student who left after the incident) would jeopardize Wheaton&rsquo;s chances of a strong season.</p>

<p>I also imagine that the coaches, administrative staff, and trustees involved in this incident thought that they were right to give the players a second chance. The reasoning is familiar: boys will be boys, college students make dumb decisions, why should one bad choice ruin someone&rsquo;s collegiate sports experience?</p>

<p>But framing this as a learning opportunity — as the community service and essay seem to indicate — downplays the gravity of the students' actions. It also obscures the fact that the team itself (and its winning record) is what ultimately benefits from such minimal consequences.</p>

<p>All of this adds up to a culture in which winning is the ultimate good, and this is a culture that allows evil to thrive. I&rsquo;m sure that some of the football players were disgusted by their teammates' actions, and I hope that the five accused students understand that their actions went far beyond light-hearted hazing (if such a thing exists).</p>

<p>But I&rsquo;m also sure that some on the team were emboldened by the lack of consequences. After all, if you can kidnap a teammate, threaten him with sexual assault, and leave him blindfolded and injured in a strange location at night without losing your place on the team, what else can you get away with?</p>

<p>Wheaton&rsquo;s motto is &ldquo;for Christ and his kingdom.&rdquo; Sometimes you can serve Christ and win football games, but sometimes you can&rsquo;t. I hope that this incident reminds Wheaton not to bow to the false god of success in college football, but to remain true to Christ and his kingdom in the type of team spirit that they cultivate and in their willingness to confront sin in their midst.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-20-2017-culture-war-II</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-20-2017-culture-war-II</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Culture War: Towards a Better Way, part II</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Pantheon.jpg" alt="Pantheon" />
<figcaption>Parthenon, Rome © 2008 Maros Mraz | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Pantheon_panorama,_Rome.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en">CC-BY 2.5</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-18-2017-culture-war-I">part I</a>, I argued that in order to move beyond the culture war, we as a church need to firmly root our identity in Christ, rather than in some sort of moral exclusivity or, worse, in an opposition to culture. But what, exactly, does this mean? At the end of Monday&rsquo;s post, I suggested that the benefit of identifying primarily as a Christian is the gap it creates between us and our surrounding culture, a gap that allows for meaningful critique and engagement.</p>

<p>Now, to be clear, I&rsquo;m enough of a postmodernist to be deeply skeptical of any claim of objectivity. I&rsquo;m certainly not claiming that Christians can fully separate themselves from their broader culture; we are deeply implicated in our culture, for both better and worse. Indeed, one of the shortcomings of the culture war mentality is that it often focuses on a few areas of opposition without more carefully examining our immersion in the assumptions and values of western culture.</p>

<p>Once again, the Nashville Statement provides a prime example of the way the evangelical culture wars can focus on small constellation of issues without addressing our broader complicity in oppressive power structures. The statement itself insists that faithful Christians cannot even allow other Christians to so much as identify as gay — a position that even <a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/flight-93-nashville-statement/">conservative evangelicals</a> find too strong.</p>

<p>And yet a number of the signers of the statement both endorsed and continue to support Donald Trump, despite his staggering and continued disrespect for women. Trump embodies the sinful sexism and misogyny that permeates American culture, and yet he gets a pass as a &ldquo;baby Christian&rdquo; that actual faithful Christians don&rsquo;t. This is, of course, hypocrisy of the highest order. But it also illustrates the way that the culture wars obscure the ways in which the church is complicit with the powers of evil and injustice in the world.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m using the Nashville Statement as a recent example, but it&rsquo;s a single illustration of a broader problem rather than a unique instance. And to make the point once again, it is somewhere between difficult and impossible to extract ourselves from our cultural context. But if our primary allegiance is to the kingdom of God, we need to think carefully about how our cultural assumptions and values conflict or mesh with the values of Christ&rsquo;s coming kingdom.</p>

<p>Because modern western culture has been shaped, in many ways, by Judeo-Christian values, because even non-western societies exhibit what theologians have called &ldquo;natural law,&rdquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and because I believe that the line between good and evil runs through all of us, no culture is going to be wholly evil. But because evil is present in the world, and the church is in the world, the church will be implicated in evil.</p>

<p>Our job is to carefully sift between the two, identifying the good in our cultures and the evil in our midst. We should also, of course, do the opposite — but it&rsquo;s seductively easy to point to the evil outside and the good inside. How can we speak prophetically to our culture, identifying the evils that cause harm and suffering, if we refuse to examine ourselves for those very evils?</p>

<p>This is abstract, but one specific example is sexism. Now, most Christians (there are exceptions) would agree that the sort of sexism that sees women as inherently less than men is wrong. But in myriad ways the church — both evangelical and mainstream — is terrible at actually encouraging women to be full participants in the life of the church.</p>

<p>As a more progressive Christian, it&rsquo;s easy to point my finger at complementarian churches that actively discourage women from using their gifts of teaching and leadership, or at least using those fully. But across denominations — including mainstream ones — only 10% of senior pastors are women. This means that even churches that theoretically affirm the full participation of women often do a poor job of addressing the underlying sexism that prevents women from reaching leadership positions.</p>

<p>And if we don&rsquo;t have the will to address sexism in our midst because doing so reveals assumptions and attitudes that make us uncomfortable, how can we speak to the oppression of women outside the church? Additionally, addressing sexism in the church means that we need to listen to feminist thinkers — many, if not most, of whom are now outside the church. But their insights are vital to understanding how we participate in and reinforce sexism, and how we can begin to end the oppression of patriarchy. And in the absence of a robust critique of sexism from within the church, we must partner with those outside it who also seek to end the oppression of patriarchy.</p>

<p>When we commit to modeling ourselves and our churches on Jesus, we put ourselves at an angle to our culture. But this doesn&rsquo;t mean war; rather, it places us in a unique position to speak to the evils of oppression and injustice. Existing at an angle to culture, however, does not mean that we are removed from it. So in order to maintain our witness, we must acknowledge the ways in which we participate in the evils of the world and be willing to amplify those outside the church who are also working against the powers of evil in the world.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Cultures worldwide and throughout time have had prohibitions on things like murder and theft, showing a certain baseline morality or ethics that humans in general share.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-18-2017-culture-war-I</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-18-2017-culture-war-I</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2017 10:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Culture War: Towards a Better Way, part I</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure class="float-right">
<img src="/assets/blog_images/trinity_church.jpg" alt="Trinity Church" />
<figcaption>Trinity Church, New York City | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Trinity_Church_New_York_City.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>In reading and writing about last month’s Nashville Statement, I’ve been thinking more broadly about the idea of a culture war. That statement is certainly another salvo in the ongoing conflict between the evangelical church and American culture, but like many other former or disaffected evangelicals I’m weary of the so-called culture wars. In my experience, this conflict isn’t helpful; it doesn’t help to build relationships, nor does it result in meaningful critiques of contemporary American culture.</p>

<p>I’m not going to spend this post attacking the culture wars, however. It’s tempting, but engages in exactly the flaw I want to critique: an inability to lovingly engage with someone who differs with, or is opposed to, my own beliefs. Instead, I want to think about ways forward, ways of moving beyond a culture war mentality. How can we have a faithful Christian witness without waging a culture war?</p>

<p>First, a brief summary of my position on the church in the world — since Christians have legitimate disagreements about how the two ought to relate to one another. I believe that the church ought to be interacting with the broader culture, rather than withdrawing from the world like the Amish (or Rod Dreher’s Benedict option). I also believe that the church should also stand distinct from the surrounding culture, finding a balance between withdrawal and assimilation. I see the church as distinct from the culture around it, but not removed from that culture.</p>

<p>But what is it that makes the church distinct? We must first answer this question, because without an idea of what makes us distinct we cannot consider how to best manifest that distinction within our particular cultural contexts.</p>

<p>I think the simplest, yet most profound, answer to the question of what makes us distinct is Jesus. We’re marked by our belief in him as Savior, by our belief (as we say in the eucharistic liturgy) that Christ has died, Christ is risen, and Christ will come again. Christians believe, as Paul says in <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=romans+10:9&amp;version=NIV">Romans</a>, that Jesus is Lord and that he has been raised from the dead.</p>

<p>But what does that even mean? Isn’t there more to our identity as Christians than affirming that Jesus is Lord and that he has been raised from the dead?</p>

<p>Well, yes — but it still comes back to Jesus. <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Romans+13:14&amp;version=NIV">Paul</a> tells us <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=galatians+3:26-28&amp;version=NIV">twice</a> to clothe ourselves in Christ as we strive to live as Christians. John takes a slightly different angle, focusing on the love of God that is to flow through us; he <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+John+3:23&amp;version=NIV">writes</a> that we are to believe in Jesus and love one another. Throughout the New Testament, the qualities we are to cultivate are those modeled by Christ and received through the Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>And if we turn to Jesus himself, he tells us that all the law and the prophets are summed up in two <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew+22:34-40&amp;version=NIV">commands</a>: love God and love your neighbor. This sounds simple, but living into these commands is the work of a lifetime.</p>

<p>I don’t want to pretend that this is a simple, or an easy, answer to the question of what it is that makes the church distinct. We may agree that it’s Jesus, but what does that look like? How is it distinctive? And how should a life patterned on Jesus differ from the surrounding culture? Even New Testament writers like Paul and Peter draw on the Roman household codes as models for orderly relationships, indicating that the church’s moral standards may have significant overlap with the standards of its surrounding culture.</p>

<p>But the advantage of patterning our lives, our distinctiveness as Christians, on Jesus is that it frees us from comparisons to the surrounding culture. Imitating Christ may align us with cultural values or put us in opposition to them, and our call is to hold fast to Christ regardless.</p>

<p>I don’t mean to suggest that we can ever fully separate ourselves, Christian or otherwise, from the culture in which we live. But the great advantage of Christianity, in my mind, is the gap it creates between Christian and culture, since our ultimate allegiance is to Christ and his kingdom. In Wednesday’s post, I’ll turn to this gap and suggest some ways in which it can provide a model of cultural engagement beyond culture war.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-15-2017-men-and-emotion</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-15-2017-men-and-emotion</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Men, Emotion and King Arthur</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Garrick_Arthur.jpg" alt="Death of Arthur" />
<figcaption>John Garrick, <i>The Death of King Arthur,</i> 1862 | via <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:The_Death_of_King_Arthur_by_John_Garrick.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Earlier this summer, the New York Times ran an article titled <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/06/15/well/family/talking-to-boys-the-way-we-talk-to-girls.html?_r=0">“Talking to Boys the Way We Talk to Girls.”</a> This article examines how parents and caregivers tend to limit the emotional vocabulary of boys, sending the message that boys need to develop emotional distance and stoicism. As the title suggests, the piece ends with a call to engage boys as well as girls emotionally — to let them experience and talk through emotions.</p>

<p>The examples in the article, and its modest call to support young boys as they experience and process the whole array of human emotions, won’t be revelatory to anyone who has reservations about modern American notions of masculinity. I read the article, nodded in agreement, and then I made the cardinal mistake of the internet.</p>

<p>I read the comments.</p>

<p>Although I shouldn’t have been surprised, a number of commenters — perhaps as many as half — expressed concern or even outrage over their perception that this article aimed to turn boys into girls. Many of these concerned comments noted that boys and girls are different, and argued that feminizing boys would create vague social ills.</p>

<p>These comments, of course, rehash the denigration of anything labelled “feminine” (including emotions) while also misunderstanding the article — which simply pointed out that we should teach both boys and girls emotional literacy, rather than attempting to restrict or suppress boys’ emotions (the article also pointed out that boys experience emotions, which should be unexceptionable but apparently isn’t).</p>

<p>These critical comments about the article also tended to reflect the prominence of what I’ll call the “Clint Eastwood” model of masculinity. This model prizes emotional distance in relationships and a stoic acceptance of circumstances; emotional reactions (or at least, reactions other than anger) are for women, not for men who want to be accepted and successful.</p>

<p>This model of manhood is open to critique on many levels, but I want to take a slightly different angle by looking at historical ideas of masculinity. Many of the comments on the article seemed to assume that men are naturally unemotional; ideal manhood, then, must exclude most emotions. However, ideal manhood has shifted in different cultures and times, and I want to look at just one example from the European middle ages.</p>

<p>Think, for a moment, of an ideal medieval man: I’m guessing that you thought of a knight in armor, on horseback, perhaps slaying a dragon. Maybe you thought of a real person, like Richard I (the Lionheart); perhaps you thought of King Arthur and his knights of the Round Table.</p>

<p>King Arthur and his knights are fantastic examples of medieval masculinity, since these characters were shaped to reflect idealized medieval manhood when stories about Arthur and his knights exploded into popularity across Europe in the twelfth century.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> These knights are strong in battle; pious towards God; and courteous in their interactions with women, priests, and their social peers.</p>

<p>This form of masculinity probably remains familiar to most people. The ideals of chivalry persist today, even if they has been significantly reshaped since they emerged in eleventh century Europe. But one characteristic of these ideal medieval knights may be surprising: the frequency with which Arthur and his knights exhibit strong emotions, particularly grief.</p>

<p>For example, when Arthur’s beloved nephew Gawain dies in battle, killed by the treacherous Mordred, one version of the story <a href="http://d.lib.rochester.edu/teams/publication/benson-and-foster-king-arthurs-death">(the Alliterative <em>Morte Arthure</em>) </a>shows Arthur holding Gawain’s body in his arms as he weeps, eventually so overcome by sorrow that he faints. This does not lessen Arthur’s masculinity, but instead shows us how great a man Gawain was: his death deserves an emotional response.</p>

<p>In fact, in this version of the story, Gawain was such a great knight that his death even pierces the heart of Mordred. The worst of traitors himself retains enough humanity, enough chivalry, to be emotionally moved by Gawain’s death. Arthur and Mordred’s emotional responses to Gawain’s death do not undermine their chivalric masculinity but rather reinforce it, showing the depth of their respect for an ideal knight.</p>

<p>Lancelot also demonstrates a depth of emotion in Thomas Malory’s <em>Morte Darthur</em>, the fifteenth-century text that inspires many modern retellings of the Arthurian legends. Lancelot, for Malory, is the greatest example of medieval knighthood — despite his adulterous love for Guinevere. Malory’s Lancelot frequently demonstrates strong emotions, but one particular instance stands out to me.</p>

<p>One day, a wounded knight named Sir Urry arrives at Camelot. His wounds are severe and, under a curse, have persisted for seven years; they can only be healed by the best knight in the world. After all of the knights of the Round Table attempt to heal Sir Urry, Lancelot approaches the knight and, with only a touch, immediately heals him.</p>

<p>Rather than rejoice, however, at one more proof that he is the best, Lancelot weeps as if he were a child being beaten. Malory gives us ugly, complicated emotion: Lancelot has just failed in the quest for the grail and, against his resolve otherwise, has resumed his affair with Guinevere. And yet rather than being punished by God, he is allowed to work a miraculous healing. Is it any surprise that Lancelot exhibits strong emotion? And none of his companions say a word; his emotional reaction demonstrates his awareness of his sinful nature and his gratitude towards God that he is able to heal Sir Urry.</p>

<p>As with Arthur and Mordred in the other narrative, Lancelot’s emotion reinforces his status as a great knight. Were he not aware of his failings, were he not grateful that God still allowed him to work a miracle, were he not able to express his sorrow and gratitude, he would have been a lesser man.</p>

<p>These ideal medieval knights are hardly stoic; they publicly mourn as they experience loss or are confronted with their own sinful natures. And yet these emotions do not diminish their masculinity, do not lessen them in the eyes of medieval audiences.</p>

<p>Tracing the history of emotion and gender is, clearly, beyond the scope of a blog post. But I hope these two short examples — out of many more across time and culture — have demonstrated that idealized masculinity, even warrior masculinity, can certainly include space to experience and express emotion.</p>

<p>To be clear, I’m not suggesting a return to medieval chivalry. But it’s worth remembering that our current elevation of stoicism for men is cultural, not a reflection of biological reality. Models of manhood that we still admire, like the medieval knight, manage to incorporate emotion into masculinity.</p>

<p>Experiencing emotion is part of being human, whether male or female. Teaching boys emotional literacy can only erode their masculinity if we define masculinity in a way that excludes emotion. In reality, denying boys the opportunity to experience and express their full humanity, emotions included, denies their masculinity more profoundly than allowing them to be emotional beings does.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>It’s worth noting that Christianity has always challenged the idea that ideal men are warriors; in the medieval church, priests and monks lived out an alternative masculinity based on prayer, study and piety rather than strength in battle or sexual virility. However, this never became the dominant model for masculinity and critiques of priests and monks sometimes focused on the alleged femininity of men in religious vocations.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-13-2017-why-feminism</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-13-2017-why-feminism</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2017 08:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Why Feminism?</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/disney_princess.jpg" alt="Disney Princesses" />
<figcaption>© <a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/17396723@N00/">JLinsky</a> | via <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/17396723@N00/6502707419">Flickr</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">CC BY-SA</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>When I was in college, I was determined not to be “that girl.” You know the one — she wore eyeshadow every day, curled her hair, painted her nails, cared about fashion. The shallow, boy-crazy one. The girly one. I liked logic and strategy games, and I preferred studying to shopping.</p>

<p>Now, part of my determination to not be “that girl” came from having been homeschooled in a small town in an era before YouTube makeup tutorials. I secretly envied the mysterious ability to apply eyeliner and achieve shiny ponytails, but it also seemed to me that there were two types of girls: those who cared about such things and the (better) kind of girl who didn’t. I was influenced by Jo March primarily, but also by Harriet Vane — not conventionally attractive, but able to captivate Lord Peter Wimsey through her intelligence and passion.</p>

<p>So I eschewed fashion, resigned myself to hopeless crushes, and spent Sunday afternoons playing Risk with my guy friends. I had a small group of girlfriends, but I was always reluctant to form friendships with girls who I judged as being too girly, not Serious and Smart like me.</p>

<p>At the time, I didn’t examine my preference for guy friends over girlfriends or question my assumption that “girly” was not only inferior but incompatible with smart. I did gain new friends in graduate school, though — girlfriends this time, including amazingly smart women who wore high heels and knew how to use mousse. I started, slowly, rethinking my assumption that traditionally “girly” things indicated a certain weakness.</p>

<p>It took me years to fully understand that my disdain of things pink and frilly was more than a personal preference and instead a reflection of internalized patriarchy. In western patriarchy, reason is superior to emotion and ideas superior to things — and men are associated with reason and ideas, women with emotion and the material world. I never experienced gender dysphoria, but I intuited from a young age that masculinity was superior to femininity and I shaped my interests accordingly.</p>

<p>Feminism has helped me to see the ways in which our ideas about masculinity and femininity affect all of our lives, regardless of whether we face blatant sexism. The denigration of things female, like “girly” interests in fashion or home decor, harms both women and men: men — even little boys — are discouraged from enjoying sparkly clothes and shiny nail polish, and at a deeper and more harmful level, discouraged from understanding and expressing their emotions.</p>

<p>In some ways, girls have it easier; they can enjoy both princesses and dinosaurs. But we still in many ways expect women to be more like men. Just listen to James Cameron’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2017/aug/24/james-cameron-well-never-be-able-to-reproduce-the-shock-of-terminator-2?CMP=twt_a-film_b-gdnfilm">recent criticism</a> of <em>Wonder Woman</em>. He calls her an “objectified icon,” and compares her to <em>The Terminator’s</em> Sarah Connor: “Sarah Connor was not a beauty icon. She was strong, she was troubled, she was a terrible mother, and she earned the respect of the audience through pure grit.”</p>

<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/wonder_woman.jpg" alt="Wonder Woman" />
<figcaption>© 2017 <a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/bagogames/">BagoGames</a> | via <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/bagogames/35000974642">Flickr</a> | <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">CC BY-SA</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Strong. Troubled. Terrible parent. Earned respect through grit. How many male characters could that apply to? And nothing against Sarah Connor — she rocks. But apparently for Cameron, Diana’s beauty and her compassion for humanity (and perhaps her idyllic, if unconventional, childhood) make her a poor role model for women. To be more clear: her <em>feminine</em> characteristics make Wonder Woman a “step backwards” in the representation of women on the silver screen.</p>

<p>I’m still not much of a fashion and makeup girl, and I’m okay with that. But I no longer see a perfect cat eye as a sign of shallow character, and I hope my daughters can value femininity in all its forms.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-11-2017-ACNA</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-11-2017-ACNA</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 08:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>The Pain of Exclusion: the ACNA and the Ordination of Women</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/eucharist_2.jpg" alt="Eucharist" />
<figcaption>Image from <a href="https://pixabay.com/en/communion-host-christ-jesus-church-2110404/">Pixabay</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>On Friday, the Anglican Church of North America (ACNA) released its statement on the ordination of women, following a 5-year study. This statement essentially affirms the status quo: individual dioceses retain the ability to accept or reject women’s ordination, while women remain barred from the office of bishop.</p>

<p>As a long-time member of ACNA churches, some for and some against the ordination of women, I have many thoughts. First, I am glad that the ACNA did not come out against ordaining women; second, I understand the impulse to value unity over uniformity and leave this decision up to each diocese.</p>

<p>But as much as I sympathize with the ACNA leaders who don’t want to precipitate a split (as either wholly affirming or denying women’s ordination could do), I am also disappointed. While this is a theoretical issue for the male bishops deliberating the question, it’s not a theoretical issue for me, a woman.</p>

<p>I am angry and disappointed that the matter of my full inclusion in the life of the church isn’t worth taking a stand on.</p>

<p>I’m angry that the Council of Bishops can’t see that it’s sinful patriarchy that has led the church to see <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+timothy+2:11-15&amp;version=NIV">1 Timothy 2:12</a> as a blanket prohibition for all times and places, while ignoring the literal <a href="http://juniaproject.com/who-was-junia/">writing out</a> of the apostle <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=romans+16:7&amp;version=NIV">Junia.</a></p>

<p>I am disappointed that Council of Bishops say in their <a href="http://www.anglicanchurch.net/?/main/page/1519">statement,</a> “We agree that there is insufficient scriptural warrant to accept women’s ordination to the priesthood as standard practice throughout the Province.” There may be no formally ordained New Testament women — but are there any formally ordained New Testament men? The qualifications for leaders in <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Timothy%203&amp;version=NIV">1 Timothy</a> and <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Titus%201&amp;version=NIV">Titus</a> are about as close as we come to ordination requirements, although that terminology isn’t used, and 1 Timothy includes requirements for women as well as men.</p>

<p>I am sad that, while the Council of Bishops would affirm that there is no male or female in <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Galatians+3:28&amp;version=NIV">Christ</a>, they allow a division between male and female in the Church. And moreover, that as they allow this divide they ignore the many women in the New Testament honored by both Jesus and Paul for their work in the church.</p>

<p>Jesus honors and elevates women at every step of his ministry, from the Samaritan woman at the well who proclaims Jesus as the <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=john+4&amp;version=NIV">messiah</a> to Mary, sister of Martha and Lazarus, who learns at Jesus’ <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Luke+10:38-42&amp;version=NIV">feet</a>, to Mary Magdalene, the apostle to the <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=John+20:11-18&amp;version=NIV">apostles.</a></p>

<p>In his letters, Paul greets and commends both men and women for their work in the churches. Paul praises Timothy’s mother and grandmother for their faith that they have taught to Timothy. Priscilla and Aquila travel and evangelize with Paul, and there’s no indication that Priscilla’s role is different from her husband’s.</p>

<p>I’m disappointed that the Council of Bishops defers to traditional patriarchy, referring to ordaining women as “recent innovation” rather than embracing the spirit of Paul and Jesus who invited women to participate fully in the life of the church.</p>

<p>I’m sad because, despite all their protestations otherwise, this position tells me that I, and my daughters and sisters and aunts and friends, are lacking in the eyes of God. We lack the proper anatomy for certain, perhaps even the moral stature of men.</p>

<p>And if we don’t lack, then those who oppose women’s ordination are telling me that God is arbitrary. For no reason other than biology, neither I nor my sisters can consecrate the elements, can lead the church as priest or bishop.</p>

<p>How am I supposed to understand that as the will of a loving God, of a God who created woman and called her very good? Of a Jesus who loved and honored and elevated women?</p>

<p>I understand the desire for unity. The ACNA is still in formation, and a split could be catastrophic. I don’t plan on leaving the Anglican church over this.</p>

<p>But I still mourn.</p>

<p>I mourn the patriarchy that has limited women in the church for centuries. I mourn the lack of empathy, the lack of understanding of how this position makes women feel inferior, unwanted in the church. I mourn the ways in which my sisters’ gifts are denied or constrained.</p>

<p>And I will continue to work towards the full inclusion of women in the church, the recognition that we, too, are daughters of God and co-heirs with Christ.</p>

<p>(For resources on women in the church, I highly recommend <a href="https://www.cbeinternational.org">Christians for Biblical Equality</a> and the <a href="http://juniaproject.com">Junia Project</a> as starting points.)</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-08-2017-Nashville-Statement</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-08-2017-Nashville-Statement</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 12:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>The Nashville Statement and the Primacy of Biological Sex</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><figure>
<img src="/assets/blog_images/Nashville_skyline_2009.jpg" alt="Nashville" />
<figcaption>© 2009 <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Kaldari">Kaldari</a> | via <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/08/Nashville_skyline_2009.jpg"> Wikimedia Commons</a></figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>The last week in August, the Council for Biblical Manhood and Womanhood released the Nashville Statement, a document on human sexuality that condemns homosexuality and transgenderism, and further makes this condemnation an essential faith issue. (This is rather rich from an organization that allows for a diversity of views on the Trinity, including views that have been condemned as heretical for more than 1500 years, but I digress.)</p>

<p>The response has been swift and widespread. In my own Twitter feed I saw not only Rachel Held Evans and Sarah Bessey responding but also Roxane Gay and John Scalzi. Counter-statements have been written, such as the <a href="http://www.theliturgists.com/statement/">Liturgists Statement</a>, spearheaded by Mike McHargue and Michael Gungor, and the <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/nadiabolzweber/2017/08/the-denver-statement/">Denver Statement</a>, put together by Nadia Bolz-Weber and her church, House for All Sinners and Saints.</p>

<p>The Nashville Statement is damaging on many levels, although it crystalizes rather than changes what many evangelicals have been teaching for years. These teachings have harmed individuals and their families, and the statement ignores that pain in order to condemn any sexuality outside of cis-gender heterosexuality — and elevate that condemnation to an essential tenet of faith.</p>

<p>We can, and should, talk about how this statement ignores the lived experience of LGBTQ Christians. But we also need to think about why LGBTQ issues are at the heart of this statement — why condemn sexual orientation in explicit detail while leaving issues of pornography addiction and sexual abuse to fall into a broad condemnation of sexual immorality?<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> The answer, I think, lies in the conviction of the Council for Biblical Manhood and Womanhood that the core of our personhood lies in our biological sex.</p>

<p>A close reading of articles 4 and 5 from the statement underscore the primacy of biological sex:</p>

<blockquote><p>Article 4</p>

<p>WE AFFIRM that divinely ordained differences between male and female reflect God’s original creation design and are meant for human good and human flourishing.</p>

<p>WE DENY that such differences are a result of the Fall or are a tragedy to be overcome.</p>

<p>Article 5</p>

<p>WE AFFIRM that the differences between male and female reproductive structures are integral to God’s design for self-conception as male or female.</p>

<p>WE DENY that physical anomalies or psychological conditions nullify the God-appointed link between biological sex and self-conception as male or female.</p></blockquote>

<p>Article 4 seems to affirm the uncontroversial idea that God created humanity in two separate biological sexes. Yet the phrasing “divinely ordained differences” immediately sets off warning bells — and the denial that differences result from the Fall cements that this article isn’t talking just about biological sex, as to the best of my knowledge no theologian has argued that biological sex came after the fall.</p>

<p>For the writers of the statement, God creates not only biological differences but also other differences between men and women. Those are undefined here, but anyone familiar with the work of CBMW or complementation theology can fill in the blanks. Men lead, women submit; men are rational and goal-driven, women emotional and relational; men provide, women nurture. In order to flourish as humans, this statement asserts, we must accept those differences.</p>

<p>Article 5 focuses specifically on biological sex, abandoning vague “differences” in order to assert that “reproductive structures” are “integral to God’s design for self-conception as male or female.” This article most obviously makes transgender people sinful, since their self-conception of gender is at odds with their biological sex.</p>

<p>But if we examine these two articles together, we see that it’s not only identifying as transgender that undercuts God’s purpose, but also rejecting any of the “divinely ordained differences” between men and women.</p>

<p>To be clear, I don’t want to undercut the damage this theology does to transgender individuals, who are already at a hugely increased risk of violence and suicide. But this view of transgender individuals arises from a conviction that <em>gendered</em> differences — not just <em>biological</em> differences — are created by God. Someone who does not identify with their birth sex, in this view, clearly rejects “divinely ordained difference,” and so does a woman pastor or stay-at-home father.</p>

<p>Thus, the Nashville Statement can’t address what I see as the much more concerning sexual immoralities in the church: the way that purity culture demeans both men and women, the concern for the reputation of the abuser rather than the well-being of the abused, the lack of any teaching on consent. In the world of CBMW, sexual sins are bad, but they don’t represent a perversion of the created order like same-sex attraction or gender dysphoria.</p>

<p>For CBMW, this perversion of the created order arises from a refusal to accept differences between men and women. As the Preamble states in its opening paragraph:</p>

<blockquote><p>It is common to think that human identity as male and female is not part of God’s beautiful plan, but is, rather, an expression of an individual’s autonomous preferences. The pathway to full and lasting joy through God’s good design for his creatures is thus replaced by the path of shortsighted alternatives that, sooner or later, ruin human life and dishonor God.</p></blockquote>

<p>In addition to dramatically misunderstanding the theory of gender performativity (in which “autonomous preference” has only a small role), this suggests that the greatest moral challenge facing the church is the failure of men and women to find their primary identity in their biological sex, which in turn dictates the acceptable expression of gender.</p>

<p>Think about that for a moment. In order to flourish, we must find our identity not in our shared humanity, not even in Christ, but in our genitalia. And further, in the ability of that genitalia to determine our attractions, our talents, our spiritual gifts, our place within society.</p>

<p>This results in hurtful attitudes towards our LGTBQ brothers and sisters. But it also hurts all of us by insisting that we are not human together, we are not one in Christ. We are male and female above all else.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Article 9 states: “sin distorts sexual desires by directing them away from the marriage covenant and toward sexual immorality— a distortion that includes both heterosexual and homosexual immorality.”  <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <link>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-06-2017-Introduction</link>
            <guid>http://www.intoresurrection.com/2017/09/09-06-2017-Introduction</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 20:47:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <author>Sarah Lindsay</author>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Living into resurrection: as Christians, we are called to put off the old sinful ways and live into the new life of the resurrection. This life is breaking into the world through Christ and the church, but will not fully arrive until the return of Christ. Living into resurrection is a struggle, a learning process, a series of failures — but what we are called to do.</p>

<p>While all Christians are called to live into resurrection, the idea behind this blog is to explore what this means for those of us who are discontent with evangelicalism. We’re sure about Jesus, but weary of culture wars; we’re politically engaged, but unwilling to equate conservatism with faithful Christian witness; we’re thinking about sin, but on structural as well as personal levels.</p>

<p>I’m right in this journey, so this isn’t the place to find answers. But I believe that asking the right questions is often more important than finding the right answers, so I envision this as a place for working through the questions that arise as I work towards living out my faith.</p>

<p>As is probably clear already, I’m particularly interested in orthopraxy, in putting faith into action. Actions spring from beliefs, so orthodoxy is also important — but I will be thinking through the cycle in which our beliefs influence our actions, which then in turn shape our beliefs. To put it a little differently, I’m interested in how authority (beliefs) and experience (actions) interact and inform one another.</p>

<p>The divide between authority and experience, or reason and emotion, pervades western culture — with authority and reason most often given preeminence over experience and emotion. But as an embodied human being with a rational mind, I can’t pretend that my experiences and actions matter less than my reason or are wholly subordinate to authority and logic.</p>

<p>The bodily resurrection of Christ shows the redemption of our whole selves: bodies as well as souls, emotions as well as reason. So as we live into the resurrection, it’s not enough to simply have a set of right beliefs, the right mental framework. That mental framework must affect our actions and must in turn respond to and benefit from our own embodied experience.</p>

<p>That’s all very theoretical. But practically, as we live into resurrection, what does it mean to put off sin? What does it mean to act justly, to love mercy? How do we love others as ourselves, let alone love our enemies? American society at this particular moment calls out for answers. Racial injustice, sexism and misogyny, and economic oppression demand an embodied theology, demand beliefs that produce action.</p>

<p>I’m still working on that myself. Growing up in the evangelical church, faith seemed to be mostly about believing the right things and living a morally good life. Church members prayed for each other, brought meals to the ill and donated to foreign missions, but personal spiritual growth always seemed to be the dominant goal. Sin was mainly personal, and the resurrection meant that we get to go to heaven when we die.</p>

<p>At a certain point, though, I began to rethink this approach to Christianity (largely thanks to the work of N.T. Wright). If sin is bigger than just me, and resurrection is bigger than just me — Christianity must also be much bigger than just me. Over the last decade, I have been in the process of reframing my Christianity as participating in God’s resurrection work in the world, a work that goes far beyond me as an individual.</p>

<p>As part of this journey, I have become a feminist. I’m still learning about issues of race in America, but I am committed to the work of racial justice. I affirm the dignity and worth of those who identify as LGBTQ. I mourn the economic forces that keep many in poverty. I am trying to learn what it means to be a Christian and to love my neighbor, to act justly, to seek mercy.</p>

<p>If this is also your journey — whatever your starting point — I hope that we can walk together for a while as we strive to live into resurrection.</p>]]></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
